<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse about Christ and antichrist, or, A demonstration that Jesus is the Christ from the truth of his predictions, especially, the coming and the seduction of antichrist : to which is added a treatise about the resurrection / by Edward Bagshaw ...</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37055</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16197803</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16197803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105048</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1085:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse about Christ and antichrist, or, A demonstration that Jesus is the Christ from the truth of his predictions, especially, the coming and the seduction of antichrist : to which is added a treatise about the resurrection / by Edward Bagshaw ...</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Simon Miller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 59.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apologetics.</term>
               <term>Truth --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
               <term>Faith and reason.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105048:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105048:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE ABOUT CHRIST AND ANTICHRIST: OR, A DEMONSTRATION THAT Jeſus is the Chriſt, From The Truth of His PREDICTIONS, Eſpecially, The Coming and the Seduction of ANTICHRIST. To which is added, A TREATISE about the RESURRECTION.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Edward Bagſhaw</hi> Stu. of Ch. Ch. in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Simon Miller,</hi> at the Star in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1661:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105048:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105048:2"/>
            <p>INSIGNISSIMIS ET Fidaei Chriſtianae Studioſiſsimis Viris, HUMPHREDO WYNCH, Equiti &amp; Baronetto, ET JOHANNI BROWNE, Armigero; Opellam hanc, De JESU &amp; RESURRECTIONE, Religionis noſtrae Fundamenta confirmantem, ET Piis, uti ſperat, omnibus non inutilem futuram AUTHOR Sui amoris ac obſervantiae ergo D. D. C. Q.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edwards Bagſhawe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:105048:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105048:3"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Chriſtian and Candid Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Diſputes and Controverſies in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, have multiplied themſelves into many large and tedious Volumes, yet, I believe, Chriſtian Reader, thou wilt eaſily agree with me, that were but one Queſtion rightly ſtated, and throughly believed, moſt other might ſafely be neglected by us, as Uſeleſs and Impertinent. And the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is this, <hi>Whether the Scriptures be the Word of God;</hi> or, to uſe an Expreſsion, which will give no Party offence, <hi>A full and perfect declaration of Gods Will.</hi> Were this but once really aſſented to, who doth not ſee, that all Additionals are either Impious, or, elſe, at the beſt, but needleſs and unneceſſary Appendixes: much like rotten and painted Poſts, affixed unto a ſtately Edifice; which do not only deface the Beauty of the Building, but likewiſe make the ſtrength of it to be ſuſpected. Since Scripture, if it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it did come from God, doth beſt alone, without the leaſt mixture of Humane Inventions to underprop it.</p>
            <p>This therefore is that great thing, which in this following Treatiſe I have undertaken to demonſtrate, in a Method, if my Reading and Obſervation fail me not, which none have attempted before me: For whereas there are two waies, by
<pb facs="tcp:105048:4"/>which men ordinarily do come to be aſcertained of the Truth of Scripture: The one, by an Inward Experimental Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; the other, by an Argumentative and Rational Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; The firſt of theſe I have altogether waved, becauſe though Experience be an Infallible Argument to him that hath it, yet it is not a Demonſtration that can be improved to the Conviction of another; And therefore I have appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf wholly unto the ſecond way of Proof; wherein dealing with men as men; and enlarging upon thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and known Principles of Reaſon, that all acknowledge; the Unbeliever, muſt find ſome ſtronger Arguments, than any I have yet met with, to juſtifie himſelf by; or elſe, with me, be won over to the Obedience of the Faith of Chriſt. I do not ſpeak this, as if I thought it poſsible for any Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or Art of Man to perſwade another to believe: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Poize,</hi> to which the mind is brought by a ſober and calm debating the matter on both ſides, is that way by which the Spirit of God in Inquiſitive men doth uſually prepare an Entrance for Faith; for the ſtrong man must firſt be caſt out, and every Objection ſingled out and diſarmed, before a ſtronger than he can enter in. And this, Chriſtian Reader, is the very utmoſt deſign of this ſmall Treatiſe, which I had never publiſhed, but that I thought it my duty, to impart unto others that ſatisfaction which I my ſelf have received. If there be any that make another In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and from what I have ſpoken concerning <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> (wherein I have uſed the very Language, and, ſo far as I underſtand it, the ſenſe of Scripture) will infer, that I am either for, or againſt any of the Parties, who now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about their ſeveral Forms of Worſhip: They will wrong me very much, but themſelves more; ſince the misjudging of others is an Uncharitable Preſumption which is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible
<pb facs="tcp:105048:4"/>with a Christian Temper. What my Judgement is concerning Epiſcopacy, and how ſutable to right Reaſon and Scripture that Order is, I have already aſſerted? And I think none are greater Enemies to Biſhops than thoſe who ſeek to eſtabliſh them, by pleading a Neceſsity of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which whether they may at all be uſed, is a Queſtion: but that they may very ſaſely be diſuſed, is no Queſtion at all. It is therefore liberty in ſmall things alone that I have formerly and do yet plead for; and that upon this ſingle Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, becauſe I think Chriſt came to ſet his Church free from all unneceſſary Yokes; and therefore it doth not lye in the power of any man to bring them into bondage again: And let but any ſober diſintereſſed perſon convince me once that the Church (<hi>i.e.</hi> where the State is Chriſtian the civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate) hath power to impoſe in Religious Worſhip, and I ſhall then ſo far alter my Judgment, as inſtead of being troubled that we are gone thus far, be very ſorry that we go no farther in our conformity. But till then, it is my conſtant Prayer, That, if our Rulers will ſtretch their Power, to make ſome Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny between the Chriſtian and the Civill State, all men may quietly ſuffer for what they cannot chearfully ſubmit to; without making any more noiſe in the World, than what a calm and diſpaſsionate debate of Truth may amount to. Had this Courſe at firſt been taken, we ſhould not have had ſome cry down <hi>Dagon,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Baal-Berith, i.e</hi> ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, if not worſe, diſplace ſuperſtition; and exerciſe a greater Tyranny than that which they complained of. But I leave this ſad Argument, and entreat thee, Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to look upon me as one, that, by the goodneſs of God, can call himſelf a Chriſtian in the moſt large and comprehenſive Notion of the Word, according to our Saviours explication, <hi>Whoever is not againſt Chriſt, is for him;</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb facs="tcp:105048:5"/>I ſee the least appearance of ſincerity and uprightneſs, though in Perſons differing from my ſelf in Judgement, I can preſerve my own opinion, without the leaſt prejudice to that Charity I ow Mankind in general, or that endearedneſs of Affection which is particularly due to all ſorts of Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, though miſtaken, Chriſtians. With this Confeſsion I cloſe my Preface, and diſmiſs thee to the Book it ſelf; which I deſire may be read, as it was writ, with a ſingle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced mind. And if thou findeſt anything of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by it, give God the glory, who hath made uſe of a very unlikely Inſtrument to do thee good by: But if in any place thou findeſt my Reſoning doth not ſeem Cloſe and Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, let me know my Errour, and I ſhall think my ſelf more obliged to thee for thy ſerious reproof, than for thy partial and unweighed Commendation. <hi>Farwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDW. BAGSHAWE.</signed> 
               <dateline>Chriſt Church in <hi>Oxon.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 21. 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105048:5"/>
            <head>A Demonſtration that JESUS is the CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOH. 13.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now I tell you of it before it come to paſs, that when it doth come to paſs, you may know that I am.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the words of our Saviour, ſpoken by way of Inference or Uſe from the Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had made concerning the Treachery of <hi>Judas;</hi> for, as we find, <hi>v.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The devil having already put, or caſt, it into the heart of</hi> Judas <hi>to betray him,</hi> our Saviour warns his Diſciples of it, even while they ſate at Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with him; and firſt he tells them in general Terms, that <hi>they were not all clean, v.</hi> 10. (to which the Evangeliſt adds by way of Comment, <hi>for he knew who ſhould betray him, therefore he ſaid, ye are not all clean,</hi> v.11.) and then more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly our Saviour explaines what this <hi>Uncleanneſs</hi> was, and wherein it did conſiſt; that it was, not a <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> but a <hi>Moral Uncleanneſs;</hi> not a <hi>Filthineſs of the Fleſh,</hi> but an <hi>Impurity of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105048:6"/>Spirit,</hi> for, ſaith he, <hi>He that eateth bread with me, hath lift up his heel againſt me,</hi> v. 18. i.e. <hi>ſhall betray me,</hi> as in expreſs words is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>v.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>This Crime, which had been ſtrangely horrid if a profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had done it, appeared to the Diſciples much more incredible, in that it ſhould be attemped by one of them, who knew him to be <hi>the Son of God,</hi> who had confeſſed, preached, and done Miracles in his Name; and now, in token of perfect Amity and Friendſhip, were all ſate at an Holy Banquet together; and therefore that any of their Number ſhould conſent to, nay, promote ſo great a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, ſeemed a thing almoſt Impoſſible: And therefore we find the Apoſtles did diſpute and enquire among themſelves, and were ſo much ſurprized with wonder, that they even queſtioned the Truth of their Maſters Prediction.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour knowing their Thoughts, and being willing to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe and ſettle their Inquietudes; in this Verſe he ſeems to grant that ſuch a thing was ſcarce imaginable, that one ſo related to Chriſt, ſhould yet harbour ſuch bloudy deſigns againſt him: But yet, ſaith he, as ſtrange and as incredible as it ſeems, it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come to paſs; and therefore I acquaint you with it before hand, <hi>that when it doth come to paſs, you may know that I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words, <hi>I am,</hi> are capable of a twofold Interpretation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>I am God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>I am the true Meſſiah.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, Theſe words, <hi>I am,</hi> may ſignifie, <hi>I am God;</hi> ſo when <hi>Moſes</hi> enquired after the Name of God, this ſhort Anſwer is returned unto him,
<note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> tell the people, to whom you go, that <hi>I am hath ſent thee.</hi> And therefore in the Song which <hi>David</hi> ſung for the Triumphant entry of the Arke this Name is recorded, <hi>Extoll ye the Lord by his Name Jah,</hi> i.e. <hi>I am;</hi> which implies and contains in it all the parts of ſucceſſive Beeing,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.</note> and therefore it is rendred by God himſelf, <hi>He that is that was, and that is to come, i.e.</hi> that hath one Fixed, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, Immutable Beeing. Now what God by <hi>Moſes</hi> doth barely aſſert, by <hi>Iſay</hi> he doth challenge, and demonſtrate to be his due, by thoſe two Incommunicable Properties of the Deity, <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>Power,</hi> and his <hi>Preſeience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 41.23.</note> And therefore when he diſpures his Right with the Heathen Idolls, <hi>Shew,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the things that are to come here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that we may know that ye are Gods.</hi> And in other places, he tells his people that ſuch and ſuch Judgements, which he had threatned,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105048:6"/>ſhould come upon them; <hi>And then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ye ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi> So our Saviour here, being to take his leave of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and foreſeeing how ſhrewdly their Faith would be ſhaken, ſeems to tell them: You have indeed confeſſed me to be <hi>the Son of God,</hi> and therein <hi>One</hi> with God the Father; this, if you judge of me by my outward appearance, or by the vile and cruell uſage I ſhall ſhortly undergo, muſt needs appear to be a ſtrange and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable contradiction. And therefore I leave you this Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that when you ſee it fulfilled, ye may believe that <hi>I am God</hi> indeed. And thus <hi>I am</hi> is to be underſtood, in thoſe words of our Saviour, where he doth expreſly aſſert his Divinity.
<note place="margin">Joh. 8.38.</note> 
               <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was, I am, i.e.</hi> According to my Divine Nature, by which I am from Everlaſting: Of which Nature it is that our Saviour ſpeaks to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus, None hath aſcended up into heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man who is in heaven, i.e.</hi> who is now there as God, though, as man, he be circumſcribed and limited to a place on Earth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe words, <hi>I am,</hi> may be rendred, <hi>I am the Christ,</hi> or <hi>the true Meſſiah, the Saviour of the World;</hi> whoſe coming was ſo long ago foretold and propheſied of. This will appear by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring two places of Scripture together, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.25. with <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. In <hi>Act.</hi> 13.25. the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> repeating the words of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> ſaith, <hi>As</hi> John <hi>fulfilled his Courſe, he ſaid, whom think ye that I am; I am not,</hi> which the Evangeliſt <hi>John</hi> relating, <hi>c.</hi> 3.28. makes up the ſence thus: <hi>Ye your ſelves bear me witneſs, that I ſaid I am not the Christ.</hi> Thus <hi>I am</hi> is to be underſtood in thoſe words of our Saviour to the Jews, <hi>If you do not beleeve that I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8.24.</note> 
               <hi>you ſhall dye in your ſins; i.e.</hi> If you do not believe that I am that <hi>Meſſiah</hi> who is to dye for the ſins of the World, <hi>you ſhall dye in your ſins,</hi> and take the guilt of them upon your ſelves.</p>
            <p>And thus I take the words in this place.</p>
            <p>From the words thus explained ariſe two Obſervations:</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>That our Saviour is the true Meſſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>That the way for us to be infallibly aſſured that our Saviour is the true Meſſiah, is impartially to weigh the truth of his Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>1</label> The firſt Obſervation is, That <hi>our Saviour is the true Meſſiah;</hi> and this will be of eaſie diſpatch, becauſe it is the firſt known Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Faith. I ſhall only briefly explain it. That which in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105048:7"/>Hebrew is called <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> in Greek <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in Engliſh ſignifies <hi>Anointed:</hi> And implies the ſolemn deſignation of our Saviour by God unto that great Work of Redeeming Mankind. For as in the Old Law, all that were called out unto any eminent Employment, either in Church or State,
<note place="margin">Exod. 30.23, &amp;c.</note> had an Oyl of a peculiar compoſition poured out upon them, which was a ſign of their Inauguration and Inſtallment from God into their Office. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were anointed to be <hi>Kings; Aaron</hi> and his Succeſſors were anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be <hi>Prieſts; Eliſha</hi> and ſome others were anointed to be <hi>Prophets;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15.</note> (whence is that of the <hi>Pſalmist, Touch not mine Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm,</hi> where the latter part of the Verſe doth explain the former;) ſo our Saviour, who was in a ſpiritual ſenſe to diſcharge all theſe Offices, was <hi>Anointed, i.e.</hi> filled with the Spirit of God, the gifts and graces of which were Typified by the Clearneſs and Fragrancy of Legal Oyl,
<note place="margin">Ver. 7.</note> whence that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. <hi>He hath anointed thee with the Oyl of gladneſs above thy Fellows,</hi> is by all the Jewiſh, as well as Chriſtian Expoſitors underſtood of the plentiful effuſion of the Holy Spirit, which was to be upon the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> for that of him, and not of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that Pſalm was written is clear from the foregoing Verſe, where ſpeaking of the ſame Perſon, he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Ver. 6. Heb. 1.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Throne, O God, is for ever and ever.</hi> And therefore by the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is rightly applied unto our Saviour;
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.34.</note> of whom <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> gives this Teſtimony, That <hi>God gave unto him the Spirit,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>i.e. not in that ſtinted and limited meaſure,</hi> wherein formerly it was diſpenſed, but ſuited to the Large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an Immence Donor, and to the Capacity of an Infinite Receiver; who was God as well as Man; and by that neer Union did infuſe into his Manhood whatever is conceiveable of Power, Purity, or Perfection.</p>
            <p>And that this is the meaning of <hi>Jeſus</hi> being the <hi>Chriſt, i.e.</hi> anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Spirit, two places, amongſt many other, will clear, one is that of our Saviour in his Sermon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. wherein he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies unto himſelf that paſſage in the Prophet <hi>Iſay, The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, wherefore he hath anointed me; i. e.</hi> By putting his Spirit upon me he hath abundantly fitted me for my employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Another place is that of the Diſciples, in their Prayer to God, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.27. where applying <hi>Davids</hi> words in the ſecond Pſalm unto our Saviour, <hi>Herod,</hi> ſay they, <hi>and Pilate, together with the people of Iſrael were gathered againſt thy holy Child Jeſus, whom thou
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105048:7"/>haſt anointed; i. e.</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> explains it in another place, <hi>Whom thou haſt anointed with the Holy Spirit and with Power;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.38.</note> thereby enabling and qualifying him for ſo great and weighty an undertaking. And ſo much for the firſt Obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>2</label> The ſecond Obſervation is this, <hi>That the way infallibly to prove that our Saviour is the true Meſſiah, is impartially to weigh the truth of his Predictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I addreſs my ſelf to the proof of this, I muſt anſwer an Objection, which many may be ready to make, <hi>viz.</hi> That this is a thing ſufficiently believed already, and therefore it will be only loſt labour to go about to prove it. To which I anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the greateſt part of thoſe who call themſelves Chriſtians are not ſo indeed: For as the Apoſtle ſaies of his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ſo may we ſay of moſt in our reſpective Auditories,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>All have not Faith.</hi> There being, in all places, many, too many, whoſe Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ſhould the Apoſtle have ſeen, he would have told them, as he did the <hi>Philippians</hi> weeping, That <hi>they were enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt, for their belly was their God, and they gloried in their ſhame.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.18, 19.</note> For let us not deceive our ſelves, as if Viciouſneſs and Pravity of Life, could be reconciled with Sincerity and Truth of Faith; but rather let us argue with <hi>David, The wickedneſs,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.1,</note> 
               <hi>of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſaith in my heart, there is no fear of God before his eyes; i.e.</hi> when I ſee the Actions of wicked men, I do as evidently perceive, that inwardly they fear not God, as if they did in expreſs terms pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim and avouch it. So may we, without any uncharitableneſs, conclude from the Lives of moſt Chriſtians, that their hearts are full of Unbelief: For there is ſo neceſſary, ſo inſeparable a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion between Faith and Obedience, that they can no more be ſevered than Fire and Heat. And therefore, ſince the fruits of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief are ſo apparent every where, it is our duty, not only to Preach, but to Prove <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that ſo we may root out thoſe innate and ſoul-deſtroying Seeds.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My ſecond Anſwer to that Objection, is, That the firmeſt and beſt rooted Faith is yet capable of an Encreaſe and Progreſs. He that believeth a little, ought to believe much; and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth much, may believe more; and therefore Arguments which do enforce grounds of Faith can never be unſeaſonable; for which reaſon it is, that though theſe Diſciples did believe on our Saviour, had confeſſed him, and, in token of firm affiance, did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105048:8"/>promiſe to dye with him, rather than to forſake him; yet our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour thought fit to fortifie and ſtrengthen them by yet more urging this new Motive, <hi>Sc.</hi> the event of his Predictions.</p>
            <p>Having thus cleared my way to the Doctrine, and ſhewed the neceſſity of preaching it, I affirm, That the way to be infallibly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that our Saviour is the Meſſiah, is to obſerve the Event of his Precitions; Becauſe</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> This is the way which our Saviour laies moſt ſtreſs upon, both here and in other places; here it was the very ſcope and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his foretelling the Treachery of <hi>Judas, I tell you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>before it comes to paſs, that when it doth come to paſs, you may believe that I am.</hi> And again, when he had told them of his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture,
<note place="margin">Joh. 14.29.</note> and that he would ſend the <hi>Comforter,</hi> that is, <hi>the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> to ſupply his room, and to make up their Joyes, he adds, <hi>And now I tell you before it come to paſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>that when it doth come to paſs, ye might believe.</hi> Again, when he had told his Diſciples of that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and inhumane Uſage they ſhould meet with, <hi>Theſe things,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have I told you, that when the time ſhall come, ye may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that I told you of them; i. e.</hi> And from thence gather a full and peremptory aſſurance of my Truth and Veracity. So in thoſe many Predictions, which we have in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. our Saviour ſubjoyns <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Mar. 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>but you look to it, behold I have foretold you all things.</hi> So that our Saviour, ſo often urging and inſiſting upon his Propheſies, ſeems to intimate, that he was not unwilling to venture his whole Cauſe upon the force of that ſingle Argument.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> This is the way which God himſelf did long before point to, and warrant us in the Uſe of. For he foretels by <hi>Moſes, I will raiſe them up a Prophet from among their Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>like unto thee, and I will put my words in his mouth, and he ſhall ſpeak unto them all that I ſhall command him.</hi> This Propheſie our Saviour hath a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar reſpect to throughout all this Goſpel of <hi>John,</hi> as <hi>Ch.</hi> 5.46. <hi>Had ye believed</hi> Moſes, <hi>ye would have believed me, for he wrote of me;</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.38. <hi>I came down from heaven, not to do my own will, but the will of him that ſent me.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.16. <hi>My Doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent me,</hi> which he oftentimes repeats, from whence many of the people,
<note place="margin">Ver 40.</note> who heard him, conclude, <hi>This is of a truth the Prophet; i. e.</hi> That Prophet, whoſe coming <hi>Moſes</hi> had foretold. So in that laſt Prayer which our Saviour made on earth in behalf of his Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Joh. 17.6.8.</note> he uſeth theſe words, <hi>I have manifeſted thy Name
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105048:8"/>unto the men which thou gaveſt me out of the World. For I have given unto them the words which thou gaveſt me;</hi> wherein our Saviour uſes the very expreſſions that are in the Propheſie of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any ſhould object, as the Jews did,
<note place="margin">Joh. 8.13.</note> that our Saviour <hi>bore record of himſelf, and therefore his Record was not true:</hi> At leaſt we ought to have ſome more convincing Arguments to prove his Truth, than barely his own Teſtimony. God hath, in that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Moſes,</hi> both made and anſwered that Objection: <hi>If,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Deu. 18.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſay in thy heart, how ſhall we know the word, or the Prediction, which the Lord hath not ſpoken? When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thing follow not, nor come to paſs, that is the thing which the Lord hath not ſpoken.</hi> From whence it follows by the Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, that if a thing be ſpoken in the name of the Lord, and doth come to paſs, it is a certain ſign that the Lord hath ſpoken it: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto that of <hi>Jeremy, When a Prophet Prophecieth of peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 28.9.</note> (and ſo conſequently of any thing elſe) <hi>when the word of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhall come to paſs, then ſhall the Prophet be known that the Lord hath truly ſent him.</hi> So that while we are upon this way of enquiry after the truth of our Saviour, by ſeeking whether his Predictions have been fulfilled or not, we are in Gods way, and have his advice to warrant us.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The fulfilling of Prophecies is a much more ſure and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory proof than the doing of Miracles. As in Natural things, an Argumentative and Rational evidence is more convincing than a ſenſible one; for the one depends upon an alterable Principle, that is, the temper of the Body, which is ſubject to many changes and miſtakes; but the other is bottomed upon an Eternal and Immutable Principle; <hi>i.e. Right Reaſon,</hi> which never varies, but, like Light, is alwaies in every place the ſame. Hence many Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have doubted whether <hi>Fire be hot,</hi> or, <hi>Snow be white</hi> in their own Nature, or not; becauſe were mans body leſs patible, or his Eye of another Figure, he would not feel that force in the one, nor diſcern that colour in the other. But none ever yet doubted, whether <hi>Three Angles in a Triangle were equal to two right;</hi> nor, <hi>whether all Lines drawn from the ſame Center unto the ſame Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence were equal;</hi> with many ſuch like Propoſitions, becauſe they are capable of ſuch a Demonſtration as paſſeth from the Eye into the Underſtanding. So is it in ſpiritual things, thoſe who believe any thing meerly upon the Credit of Miracles, have no firm Baſis to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105048:9"/>ground upon; becauſe (in ſpite of that received diſtinction, that the devil can do <hi>Mira,</hi> but he cannot do <hi>Miracula</hi>) our Saviour tels us, that <hi>Antichriſt ſhould do great Miracles,</hi> for ſure <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>Prodigies</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> comprehend as much ſtrangeneſs in them, as the word <hi>Miracle</hi> amounts to; And in the Law God cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions his People,
<note place="margin">Deut. 13.1, 2.</note> that if <hi>a Prophet did give a ſign or a Wonder,</hi> yet if he taught falſe Doctrine, he ſhould not be hearkned to; which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implies, that a falſe Prophet may do <hi>Miracles;</hi> ſo that he who relies wholly on them, is not certain but he may be deceived. Our Saviour therefore though he did many <hi>Miracles,</hi> yet he doth not bottome his plea to be the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> meerly upon them,
<note place="margin">Luk. 16. <hi>ult.</hi> Joh. 5 31.</note> but appeals altogether unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets;</hi> and ſo did his Apoſtles after him; and therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> after he had related that he had heard <hi>a voice from heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> whereby God owned Chriſt for his <hi>beloved Son,</hi> and commanded all <hi>to hear him,</hi> yet he concludes, that we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Propheſies recorded in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> and fulfilled by our Saviour, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a more firm and ſtable foundation</hi> of Faith than that Voice: Becauſe that was a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient, whereas the fulfilling of Prophecies is a ſtanding Miracle. Therefore as ſome argued about <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh</hi> 10.41.</note> 
               <hi>John,</hi> ſay they, <hi>did no miracle, but all things that</hi> John <hi>ſpake of this man were true;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many believed on our Saviour; So now, upon ſuppoſition that Miracles were ceaſed, (which I will never grant ſo long as I ſee daily ſupernatural effects of the Word in working Converſion, which when I was laſt here I did demonſtrate to be as great a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle,</hi> as the <hi>raiſing of Chriſt from the dead,</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth every where cite that, as the greateſt which ever God did) but if <hi>Miracles</hi> were ceaſed, yet if we find that all things which our Saviour ſaid are true: That what he foretold ſhould come to paſs, is come to paſs, then have we an undoubted Evidence that he was the <hi>True Meſsiah,</hi> and therefore to be believed and truſted in.</p>
            <p>The Uſe I make of this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> is to exhort all perſons, that they will take this method, which our Saviour hath preſcribed, and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his Predictions with their Events, aſcertain themſelves that they have not followed,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.16.</note> as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Artificially deviſed</hi> and <hi>well plotted Fables;</hi> but that they may ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.12. Joh. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>We know whom we have believed;</hi> we have ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and tried, and we find that this is indeed <hi>that Prophet which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105048:9"/>ſhould come into the World.</hi> And this ſcrutiny I earneſtly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend eſpecially to two ſorts of Perſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>Preachers of the Gospel;</hi> how unfit they are to convert others (which is the only duty and end of Preaching) who are not yet converted themſelves I need not mention. And therefore it ought to be preſumed of every <hi>Gospel Minister,</hi> that he himſelf is abundantly ſatisfied with the truth of what he delivers; and that he beſpeaks his Hearers, in <hi>Davids</hi> words, <hi>Come unto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.16.</note> all ye that are yet in your doubts, and <hi>I will tell you what God hath done for my ſoul; i.e.</hi> What means God hath uſed to free me from the ſame unbelief which is natural to all. Such an one, who is thus furniſhed, muſt not only barely Preach, but he muſt Prove: He muſt not only Inſtruct, but he muſt Convince Gainſayers, and leave the Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever without excuſe, that he may have no retreat to defend his Diſobedience, but meerly his Obſtinacy.
<note place="margin">Act. 9.20.</note> Thus did the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who as ſoon as ever he was converted, <hi>went and preached Jeſus in their Synagogues, that he is the Son of God;</hi> And again,
<note place="margin">Ver. 22.</note> ſaies the Text, <hi>The more they raged, the more confident he grew,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Arguing or ſtrongly proving that Jeſus is the very Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 28 23.</note> And thus he dealt with thoſe who came to him at <hi>Rome, He expounded unto them the Kingdom of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Teſtifying, or vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urging</hi> (as the word ſignifies, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.21.) <hi>and perſwading the things of Jeſus from morning untill evening out of the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Thus likewiſe <hi>Apollos, he taught the things of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.25.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with great exactneſs;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced the Jews with great earnestneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>proving publikely that Jeſus was the Christ.</hi> Theſe ought to be our Patterns, and it is, without doubt, one Reaſon, why the Goſpel makes ſo ſlow a progreſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not begin at the Foundation— We take no Notice, that that which mens hearts moſt riſe up againſt, is againſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> being the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore here we ſhould aime our Battery, where the Enemy of our ſouls is moſt deeply entrenched. For our Obedience to the Commands of Chriſt cannot riſe higher than our belief of the truth of Chriſt; and according as this perſwaſion is more or leſs wrought in the hearts of men, ſo will their practice be. Therefore as in Practice, Faith muſt precede Repentance, ſo in Preaching, the Doctrine of Faith muſt precede the Doctrine of Repentance: Or elſe we build without a <hi>Foundation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> and throw about our <hi>Hay</hi> and <hi>Stubble,</hi> our own Idle Fancies, which will never
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105048:10"/>
               <hi>reach,</hi> much leſs <hi>pierce</hi> the Conſcience: for all the while the heart is unconvinced it is unconverted. Now to convince others, there cannot be a better way than that which <hi>Paul</hi> conſtantly uſed, to relate the manner, and to enforce the <hi>mediums</hi> by which we were convinced our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I recommend this to <hi>Unbelievers,</hi> becauſe all the while they are ſo they lie under the danger of many ſad and dreadful Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.
<note place="margin">Deut. 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>He that hears not the Prophet,</hi> ſaith God by <hi>Moſes, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of him.</hi> And I fear the greateſt Unbeliever of us all would at that time, upon ſuch a Summons, be utterly unprovided of an Anſwer.
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.36.</note> 
               <hi>He that believes not the Son,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him; i.e.</hi> He ſhall bear his own burden, and ſhift for himſelf as well as he can, when he is to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with Eternal Vengeance, ſince there is nothing interpoſed to fence and to keep off that ſtroke; <hi>For me,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, <hi>who am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>he ſcornfully rejects and refuſes. Hereafter,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul, Chriſt will appear in flaming fire, to take vengeance of them who know not God, and who obey not the Goſpel of his Son.</hi> I know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that theſe will be derided by the <hi>Unbeliever,</hi> but if it ſhall appear, that other things every whit as incredible (nay, more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, ſince men naturally have ſome apprehenſions of future puniſhment) have been foretold by our Saviour, and are already fulfilled; If this, I ſay, can be proved, then I hope the Unbeliever will be perſwaded to ſhaked out that devill which doth blind and poſſeſs him; and ſpeedily alter his opinion, before his Caſe be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, and he find by experience, that all theſe things were ſad Truths, though his Luſt, and not his Reaſon, would not ſuffer him to hear them.</p>
            <p>To direct you in this Enquiry, take notice of, and weigh eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally theſe three Predictions of our Saviour, becauſe we are all living witneſſes of the truth and fulfilling of them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Concerning the <hi>preaching and ſpreading of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. Concerning the <hi>Deſtruction of Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>diſperſion of the Jews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. Concerning the <hi>coming and ſeduction of Antichrist.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt remarkable Prediction is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Predict. </seg>1</label> concerning <hi>the Preaching and ſpreading of the Goſpel.</hi> There are two places wherein our Saviour propheſies that <hi>his Goſpel</hi> ſhould be preached <hi>all over the World.</hi> One is in defence of the woman, who poured a coſtly ointment upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105048:10"/>his Head, <hi>Where ever,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this Goſpel ſhall be preached,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.13.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>In the whole world, there what this woman hath done ſhall be ſpoken for a memorial of her.</hi> Another place is in expreſs terms, ſpeaking of the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem: And,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.14.</note> 
               <hi>this Goſpel of the Kingdom ſhall be preached,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the whole inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited world, for a Teſtimony unto all the Gentiles, and then ſhall the end, i. e.</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, come.</hi> For the underſtanding of which Propheſie we muſt take notice of</p>
            <p n="1">1. The thing which was preached. It is called the <hi>Goſpel of the Kingdom;</hi> and what that is our Saviour explaines in his laſt words to his Diſciples when he ſent them to preach it: <hi>Thus it is written,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 24.46, 47. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38, 39. 1 Cor. 15.1, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and thus it behoved the</hi> Meſſiah <hi>to dye, and to riſe again the third day; and that in his Name ſhould be preached Repentance and Remiſſion of ſins unto all the Gentiles, beginning from</hi> Jeruſalem. So that it was a Doctrine very incredible, it being, as the Apoſtle obſerves,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>unto the Jews a ſtumbling block,</hi> (that he ſhould ſave others who did not ſave himſelf) <hi>and to the Greeks Fooliſhneſs;</hi> who could by no means endure to hear of a Reſurrection, as we find by <hi>Pauls</hi> entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Athens,</hi> as ſoon as ever he mentioned it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>they mocked and ſlighted him.</hi> So that there was little hopes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels prevailing by any Quallifications or Innate Diſpoſitions that were in mens minds to receive it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing conſiderable in this Propheſie is, the time when it ſhould begin, <hi>viz.</hi> after our Saviours death. Had our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſent his Apoſtles to preach this Goſpel in his life-time, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of his Miracles, and the unexampled Holineſs of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, might have given ſome credit and countenance to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and have facilitated its entrance; but to ſtay ſo long, till he himſelf was ſo ſhamefully put to death, and while the Fact was yet freſh in memory, then to ſend his Diſciples forth; this ſeems, to the Eye of Reaſon, a Time very unſeaſonable. Yet, to ſhew how ill Judges we are of Divine Proceedings, and, how infinitely beyond our ſhallow capacities Gods deſigns are ordered, this was the time which our Saviour both choſe and foretold: <hi>When,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8.28.</note> ſaith he, <hi>ye have lift up the Son of man, then ſhall ye know that I am;</hi> And again, <hi>When I am lift up from the Earth, I will draw all men unto me;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> When you have executed the utmoſt of your malice againſt me, in nailing me up to the Croſs, then ſhall I manifeſt, what you do not now believe, that I am the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> by drawing and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105048:11"/>gathering Followers unto me; whereupon he compares his Death <hi>to the falling of Grain into the Earth, <note place="margin">Ver. 24.</note> which doth not hear forth fruit untill it dye;</hi> intimating, that what courſe they took to extinguiſh and hinder his Doctrine he would order for its Advantage and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. And yet in humane probability this was not a proper time to preach up the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> when, with the utmoſt of virulency and ſcorn, he was ſo newly crucified.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the manner of propagating this Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>it ſhall be preached;</hi> he allowed his followers none but ſpiritual Weapons; and ſent them to ſubdue a gainſaying, reſiſting, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting world: being armed only with <hi>Preaching,</hi> and with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</hi> and therefore what is here called, <hi>The Goſpel of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3.10. Apoc. 1.9.</note> our Saviour calls in the <hi>Revelation, The word of my Patience;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> joyns the <hi>Kingdom and the Patience of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as ſignifying the ſame thing. And yet this, how improbable ſoever it ſeems, it then was, now is, and ever will be the way wherein <hi>Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> i. e. <hi>his Goſpel,</hi> is to thrive and proſper in: And whoever uſes any other Force, but the Force of Reaſon; or any other Art, but the Art of ſound Perſwaſion to gain others, he ſtrives to ſet up Chriſt the wrong way; and makes our Saviours <hi>Kingdom</hi> to be that, which at his death he denied it to be; viz.
<note place="margin">Joh. 18 37.</note> 
               <hi>A Kingdom of this World;</hi> againſt which I have elſewhere ſpoken
<note place="margin">* Sain ſhip no ground of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty.</note>.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Conſider the great Progreſs which the Goſpel made, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſhort time wherein it was to make it: For a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo ſtrange in it ſelf, &amp; ſo little advantaged by Humane Power, one would have thought, that an Age would have been little enough to ſettle it in any one Country; but that, in the ſpace of forty years, it ſhould be carried throughout the World; and in every place where it came, gather a conſiderable number of <hi>Proſelytes;</hi> this exceeds every thing, but our utmoſt wonder. And that the Goſpel was thus ſpread, even before the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (which was the time allotted for it) we have the Teſtimony of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> who asking this queſtion concerning the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews: Have they not heard? i. e.</hi> Can they lay the blame of their unbelief upon their not having heard? <hi>Verily,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>their ſound is gone out into all the Earth, and their words into the ends of all the habitable World.</hi> Wherin he applies the words of <hi>David,</hi> concerning the Sun, unto the Goſpel; which by the publike preaching of it,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105048:11"/>was then become like the Sun, in diffuſive Heat,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.5, 6. v. 23.</note> and Univerſality of Influence. Again, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> he minds them of the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e which was laid up for them in Heaven, whereof they had heard before in the word of the Goſpel of Truth: <hi>Which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is come unto you, as it is in all the world, and bringeth forth fruit, as alſo it doth among you.</hi> The ſame is yet more plain from the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> from whence it appears, that among all the Jews, not only in <hi>Judea,</hi> but throughout the world, in all <hi>Greece,</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> &amp;c. there were Churches of conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers gathered to the Faith of Chriſt, and that according to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Prophecy, before <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed. To which I might add the Teſtimony of <hi>Ioſephus, Suetonius, Tacitus,</hi> and other forraign Writers, but the cauſe needs them not.</p>
            <p>So that put all this together, a Doctrine concerning Salvation by a <hi>crucified Chriſt,</hi> and therein contradictory to all Humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. 2. A Doctrine enjoyning all poſſible ſtrictneſs and ſeverity of life, and therein little grateful or pleaſant to Humane Deſires. 3. A Doctrine excluding all force and violence, and leaving its Followers at perfect liberty, whether they would ſubmit to it or not, and therein quite contrary to worldly Arts and politick Contrivances. 4. A Doctrine, by which nothing was to be gained, but only Heaven, nothing being more certain from an enraged, becauſe unbelieving world, than the ſame cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity which befell the Author; and therein a Doctrine dangerous in Profeſſion, as difficult in Practice. And yet in ſpite of all theſe diſadvantages that it ſhould run through the World, and have Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies and Monuments of Victory, <hi>i.e. Churches</hi> behind it, in fewer years than ſome have taken barely to ſurvey and travel it; This ſhews that the Power which conducted it was as great as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which foreſaw and foretold it; that is, that they were both, Supernatural; both, Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
               </label> I cannot paſs over the fulfilling of this Prediction, without ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that they ſeem not at all to underſtand the Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Goſpel, who ſeek for ſecular Arts to uphold and ſupport it. That Doctrine, which, when the World was prejudiced and Armed againſt it, did conquer and triumph over it, needs not any encouragement from earthly motives. It is ſtill the <hi>Arm of God to Salvation,</hi> and needs not the <hi>Arm of Fleſh</hi> to back it. All the while the <hi>Christians</hi> were a divided Body from the <hi>Men of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.15.</note> they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105048:12"/>ſhone like <hi>Stars in the midſt of Darkneſs;</hi> and thoſe who came not in to them, confeſſed it was for want of Courage, and not for want of Conviction. But as ſoon as ever God ſuffered the World to come into the Church, and that Religion grew the way to Preferment: preſently what it got in power, it loſt in purity; and quickly was diſpirited, and worn out by that, which can act a part much better, and that is, <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> To wiſh that Religion may again thus thrive and proſper, is to pray that it may be undone: For our Religion was not calculated for any thing, but to ſave our ſouls; and where ever ſound convincing Preaching is protected, there is Religion ſufficiently countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> For that Propheſie, <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queens thy nurſing Mothers,</hi> doth not ſignifie any Authoritative or Imperious enjoyning even of the true Religion, but an Humble and Reverential ſubmiſſion to it, as it follows in the next words, <hi>They ſhall bow down to thee with their face toward the Earth, and lick up the duſt of thy feet, and thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord.</hi> Let Chriſtian Magiſtrates do but that part of their Duty, which is to puniſh Vice and Immorality; and where the Goſpel is planted, God will effect the ends of that without any farther aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Prediction of our Saviour is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Predict.</hi> 2.</note> concerning <hi>the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>the disperſion of the Iews:</hi> which is at large deſcribed by three of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> in their Chapters preceding our Saviours Paſſion. And though the preſent poſture and ſtate of the <hi>Iews,</hi> is a ſufficient Comment upon thoſe Chapters, and may ſeem to prevent any Enlargement, yet to make the Truth more apparant and forcible, I ſhall inſiſt upon two or three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>City,</hi> and particularly <hi>the Temple ſhould be laid even with the ground;</hi> concerning the <hi>City</hi> we have this Prediction in <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 19.42.</note> that when our Saviour <hi>ſaw the City, he wept over it, for the daies ſhall come,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the Enemies ſhall caſt a trench about thee, and ſhall lay thee even with the ground, and thy Children within thee, and they ſhall not leave in thee one ſtone upon another.</hi> Concerning the <hi>ruine of the Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.2.</note> in <hi>Matthew</hi> we read, that when the Diſciples came to ſhew our Saviour <hi>the buildings of the Temple,</hi> which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the deſcription of <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> for the State, Magnificence and ſtrength of them, were the goodlieſt buildings in the World; our Saviour replies to them: <hi>See ye not all theſe things? Verily I ſay
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105048:12"/>unto you, there ſhall not be left here one ſtone upon another, which ſhall not be thrown down.</hi> And accordingly <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">Lib. 6 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that the firſt thing which was burnt down to the ground, and that utterly againſt the will of <hi>Titus,</hi> was the Temple, upon that very month and day, as he obſerves, wherein it was formerly burnt by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi> And concerning the City, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>Destroying the reſt of the City, and digging down the Walls,</hi> Titus <hi>left only two Towers ſtanding to be monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Romane Proweſs.</hi> And that that Propheſie might to a ſcruple be fulfilled, our Hiſtorians tell us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrates,</hi> lib. 3. c. 20.</note> that in the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Julians</hi> time, when the Jews upon his entreaty went to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build their Temple, that they might offer ſacrifice again, an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in the night tore up the very Foundations of it, and made them leave off their Enterprize.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond particular is, the <hi>terrible ſlaughter of moſt of them,</hi> and <hi>the utter diſperſion and captivity of the reſt. When ye ſhall ſee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21.20, 24.</note> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Jeruſalem compaſſed about with Armies,</hi> (which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines that, that in <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi> is called, <hi>The abomination of deſolation; i. e.</hi> the abominable deſtroying Army of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans) <hi>then know that the deſolation thereof is nigh. For theſe are the daies of vengeance. And they ſhall fall by the edge of the Sword, and ſhall be led away captive into all Nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 6. c. 17.</note> Which ſlaughter the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian relates, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>The number of the ſlain exceeds all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane or Divine Vengeance;</hi> which though it be Hyperbolically ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet he reckons up a Million and ten Thouſand, which were killed in that year of the Siege; a number great, enough to juſtifie his Paſſion, at leaſt abundantly ſufficient to verifie our Saviours Predictions; and for the other part of the Propheſie, namely, <hi>their Captivity,</hi> this was partly fulfilled by <hi>Titus,</hi> who carried away and ſold near an hundred thouſand Priſoners; but more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by <hi>Adrian,</hi> in whoſe time the Jews rebelling, under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of an Impoſtor, who called himſelf <hi>Barcocheb,</hi> or <hi>the Son of the Star,</hi> they were then moſt miſerably ſlaughtered, and an <hi>Edict</hi> made by the Emperour, that the whole Nation ſhould be bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, <hi>that,</hi> ſaith my Author, <hi>none of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 4.6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not ſo much as at a diſtance, might ſee their Native Country.</hi> Then which a more cruel and barbarous, as well as unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Law, I think was never made; to diſpoſſeſs a whole Nation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105048:13"/>at a time, without diſtinction of Innocent and Criminal, or any Proviſion to guard thoſe Frontiers. But the more harſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary the proceeding was againſt them, the more clearly doth our Saviours Truth ſhine forth, who had foretold that this ſhould befall them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The laſt and greateſt evill that was propheſied of them, That the <hi>Kingdom of God ſhould be taken from them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.43.</note> Thus our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>The Kingdom of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a People that bring forth the Fruits of it.</hi> This I call their greateſt evil: for if when the <hi>Arke was taken,</hi> which was but a ſign of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Elie</hi>'s daughter called her child, <hi>Ichabod,</hi> ſaying, <hi>the glory is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from Iſrael;</hi> How much more may we call that Nation now <hi>Ichabod,</hi> for the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is departed from them; there is among them <hi>no Viſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 74.9.</note> nor in the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> words, <hi>none that knows how long?</hi> Nay, as if they had loſt their Reaſon, with their Religion, they are ſo miſerably blinded, and given up to ſuch ridiculous follies, as we cannot but both pity and ſmile at them.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adv. Celſ.</hi> l. 2. p. 60.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> ſaid of them long ſince, interpreting this Propheſie of our Saviour, This, ſaith he, we may now ſee verified, for all that is among the Jews, is only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Tales and Trifles, for they have not the light of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-knowledge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adv. Jud.</hi> c. 13.</note> And <hi>Tertullian, Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they have left the Fountain, they have hewed to themſelves broken Ciſterns,</hi> i. e. <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues among the Gentiles where they are ſcattered, in which the Holy Spirit doth not recide, which alone is the true Temple.</hi> And in this condition they now are fit objects only for our Prayers and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; and I wiſh that all Unbelievers would lay it to heart, that to ſlight the Goſpel is not a ſin that will be expiated with a little Vengeance: For I ſhall be bold to ſay, that it was not the killing of our Saviour, though a murder of a moſt execrable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition (for that our Saviour prayed might <hi>be forgiven them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23.34.</note> who, we are ſure was heard in whatever he requeſted) which brought down all that ſtorm of wrath upon them; but their peremptory and obſtinate Neglect of offered Mercy after it. This ſhall come upon them,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.44.</note> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>becauſe they have not known the time of their Viſitation, i. e.</hi> they would not lay hold upon mercy while it might be had. And therefore our Saviour graciouſly paſſing by all offences, after his Paſſion, ſends his Diſciples firſt to them, and bids them begin at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſhewed how ready he was to pardon all, by his acceptance of ſome, and waiting long for the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105048:13"/>reſt. <hi>It was neceſſary,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,
<note place="margin">Act. 13.46.</note> that the Goſpel ſhould firſt be preached to you; but ſeeing you put it from you, and judge your ſelves unworthy of eternal life, i.e.</hi> think your ſelves too good to ſtoop unto Gods method of ſaving you, <hi>loe we turn to the Gentiles.</hi> And when their malice ſtopped not there, but what they refuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they envied unto others; <hi>Who,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle obſerves,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>killed the Lord Jeſus, and their own Prophets;</hi> and <hi>likewiſe perſecuted us, forbidding us to ſpeak unto the Gentiles that they might be ſaved;</hi> then God could hold no longer, but gave the reins to his Juſtice, and now, ſaith he, <hi>the wrath is come upon them to the uttermoſt.</hi> So then, that I may conclude this Prediction with the Apoſtles exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>They were broke off by Unbeliefe, and we ſtand by Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> 
               <hi>let us not be high-minded, but fear; For if God ſpared not the Natural branches, much leſs will he ſpare us;</hi> And as Gods ſeverity to them ſets off his mercy to us, ſo the Concluſion is infallible, that <hi>unleſs we continue in that mercy, we ſhall likewiſe be cut off.</hi> What was their Fate muſt needs be ours, if we conſent to, and approve their ſin; as all the while we continue in, or fall back into unbelief, we own and defend that Crime of the Jews, and publikely proclaime that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was not the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> but that he was juſtly put to death; and this is it which makes Infidelity a ſin of ſo deep a dye, in that it doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Undervalue and diſeſteem the blood of the Covenant;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> and conceives, that it was ſhed by Chriſt not for the Remiſſion of our ſins, but for the Expiation of his own. He then that dares not ſay, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was juſtly put to death, let him forthwith believe that he was the <hi>Chriſt, i.e.</hi> the Eternal Son of God; for, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and in the maintenance of that Aſſertion he died.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the Second Prediction.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Prediction of our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Predict.</hi> 3.</note> which I ſhall inſiſt upon, is concerning <hi>the coming and ſeduction of Antichriſt:</hi> The words of the Prediction are, <hi>Then, if any ſay unto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>loe here is Chriſt, or loe there, believe them not: For there ſhall ariſe Falſe Chriſts, and Falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great Signs and Wonders, inſomuch as they ſhall deceive, if it were poſſible, the very Elect.</hi> In which Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction there are theſe things conſiderable:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Title which our Saviour gives to <hi>Antichrist:</hi> he ſpeaks of him in the plural Number, <hi>Falſe Chriſts, and Falſe Prophets;</hi> implying, that there ſhould not be one ſingle Perſon, but a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination and Conſpiracy of Deceivers. And though the Apoſtle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105048:14"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.3.</note> ſpeaking of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> calls him, <hi>The Man of ſin,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that lawleſs one.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> calls him by a ſingle name, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Antichriſt;</hi> yet I ſuppoſe that can be no more underſtood of one man, than the word <hi>Satan</hi> of one Devil; for in thoſe words of our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Mar. 3.23.</note> 
               <hi>How can Satan caſt out Satan?</hi> And, <hi>If Satan riſe up againſt himſelf and be divided, he cannot ſtand; Satan</hi> ſignifies the whole <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> if I may ſo call it, or <hi>Regiment</hi> of evill ſpirits, under ſome one Chief,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.15.</note> called in Scripture, <hi>Beelzebub:</hi> Or as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>For even as the Body is one and hath many members,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12, 12.</note> 
               <hi>but all thoſe members of that one body, though they be many, make up but one body: even ſo is Chriſt;</hi> where the Apoſtle called the whole Church, as it contains both Head and Members, by the name of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> So is <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> a collective body of many <hi>Falſe Chriſts and Falſe Prophets,</hi> united under ſome one head, for the better managing and carrying on their deſigns; order being ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that, as our Saviour obſerves, Hell it ſelf, which is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a place of Confuſion, cannot for the preſent ſubſiſt without it. But there is a twofold Order, an Order by force and conſtraint, and that is the Order of Hell and of Antichriſt; and there is an Order by Conſent, and that is the Order of Heaven and of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing obſervable in this Prophecy, is the way wherein <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould diſcover himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> by being a <hi>Falſe Prophet,</hi> ſo v. 11. <hi>Many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall deceive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> So that a <hi>Falſe Chriſt</hi> and a <hi>Falſe Prophet</hi> is the ſame thing; the latter word being explicatory of the former. And this name of <hi>Falſe Prophet</hi> is aſcribed to <hi>Antichriſt</hi> by the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> both in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1, 2. Apoc. 19.20. 2 Pet. 2.1.</note> and <hi>Revelation.</hi> It ſignifies in Engliſh a <hi>Falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> and ſo <hi>Peter</hi> expreſly mentions: <hi>There were,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Falſe Prophets among the People, ſo there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who ſhall privily bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them.</hi> In which words the Apoſtle cannot mean, that they ſhould deny the Perſon of our Saviour, (for then we could not have had any ſufficient <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to diſtinguiſh <hi>Antichriſt</hi> by, ſince the whole Jewiſh Nation, and almoſt all the Gentiles, both then did, and ſtill do they deny him;) but as among the Jews, thoſe who were Falſe Prophets, pretended highly to honour God, but yet taught lies in his Name, and ſecretly withdrew men from his ſervice: So ſhould theſe <hi>Falſe Chriſts</hi> and <hi>Falſe Prophets</hi> cry
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105048:14"/>up <hi>Chriſt</hi> in words (<hi>for,</hi> ſaith our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.5.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall come in my Name,</hi> and he tells us that at the laſt day ſome ſhall plead for themſelves, <hi>Have we not propheſied in thy Name?</hi>)
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.22.</note> But yet both in their Doctrine and Practice they ſhould directly oppoſe him; and ſet up a Religion, which ſhould have nothing in it of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, but the Name.</p>
            <p>To find out what kind of Doctrine it would be that <hi>Antichrist</hi> ſhould preach; and what kind of Practice he ſhould follow; the beſt way will be to look in Scripture, what it was that our Saviour and his Apoſtles did moſt inveigh againſt; for thoſe very things <hi>Antichriſt</hi> would ſet up and defend.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Doctrine, you will find theſe three Opinions principally condemne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Juſtification by works;</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpends al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two Epiſtles in confuring; The ſum of what he ſaies, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Poſition: <hi>We know,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>that a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but only by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt; and we have believed in Chriſt Jeſus, that we might be juſtified by the Faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law; for by the works of the Law no Fleſh can be juſtified.</hi> And whereas many captious men were apt to aſperſe this Doctrine, as if it did open a way to looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, the Apoſtle proves by his own example,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.1, 2.</note> that if rightly underſtood, it had a quite contrary effect; ſince nothing can more effectually kill ſin, than to behold it as killing Chriſt; from thence he concludes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I aboliſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 21.</note> 
               <hi>or diſanul not the Grace of Gode for if Righteouſneſs be by the Law, (i. e.</hi> can be attained by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of the Law) <hi>then did Chriſt die in vain;</hi> for what men might have got, without any ſatisfaction made in their behalf, that Chriſt needed not have died to purchaſe: And therefore he urges again, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ye are brought to nought from Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.4.</note> i.e. <hi>Chriſt is become vain to you, if you are juſtified by the Law, ye are fallen from Grace; i.e.</hi> Ye do declare ye have no need of Grace or free Pardon, becauſe you appeal to the ſentence of that Law, from the rigour of which nothing but Chriſts Death could free you. So that <hi>Juſtification by Works,</hi> as evacuating the Death of Chriſt, and rendring mens Salvation as hazardous, and uncertain, nay, Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as before our Saviours coming, is a Doctrine perſectly <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond Doctrine recorded to us for <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105048:15"/>is the <hi>Mediation of Angels;</hi> this it ſeems, under the colour that it was too bold and preſumptuous a thing for frail Man, to addreſs himſelf immediatly unto God; ſome falſe Teachers at <hi>Coloſſe</hi> did adviſe them firſt to pray unto the Angels, and make uſe of their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation to be the <hi>Internuncii</hi> and carriers of their Requeſts. This, how ſeemingly holy and modeſt ſoever the pretence were, the Apoſtle ſharply rebukes,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.18, 19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let no man Lord it over you</hi> (or, <hi>deprive you of the Prize,</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>being ſelf-willed,</hi> or <hi>wilful</hi> in humility, and worſhip of Angels, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Thruſting or climbing into things that he hath not ſeen; being raſhly puffed up by the understanding of his Fleſh; and not holding the head;</hi> where there are three Reaſons given againſt that Opinion: Firſt, that it was not Humility, as they pretended, but a wilful, ſtubborn, and fleſhly Pride which occaſioned that conceit; they preſuming to be wiſe above what was written. Secondly, That they raſhly and without warrant entred into things, which as they had not ſeen, ſo neither ought they to have medled with. Thirdly, And chiefly, that this Doctrine did detract from Chriſt, and leſſen the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of his Mediation,
<note place="margin">1 Tim 2.5.</note> who is the <hi>only Mediator between God and Men;</hi> and therefore that Doctrine, which brought in <hi>Angels</hi> as Partners with Chriſt, in that Incommunicable Prerogative, was <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The third and laſt Doctrine which I find inſiſted upon as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> is the <hi>abridging of Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> by obtruding upon the conſcience of weaker Brethren, the obſervance of things either Unneceſſary, or elſe very Inconvenient; ſuch were the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Daies and Months, and Times and Years, i. e.</hi> the old Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Feſtivals, or ſome others like them, by way of Analogy, among the <hi>Galatians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4 9. Col. 2.16.</note> which the Apoſtle ſharply reproves; firſt, calling them <hi>Weak and beggarly Elements or Rudiments,</hi> not fit to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies pored upon by Chriſtians of any growth or ſtature; and then tells them, that <hi>he fears he had loſt his time and pains among them;</hi> for he preached up <hi>Liberty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> at another Rate, which they were not to ſlight and undervalue, it being a part of our Saviours purchaſe. So when ſome,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.21.</note> among the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> began to preach up and preſcribe an uncommanded ſtrictneſs and ſingularity of Life, in thoſe words, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not,</hi> laying a great ſtreſs of Piery in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Abſtinence; he blames them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Why are ye loaded and burdened with theſe new Rites and Ordinances? which are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105048:15"/>after the Doctrine and Commandments of Men;</hi> and therefore, as they ought not to be enjoyned, ſo need they not to be any farther pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by you than ſuits with your own Convenience. Nay, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> to command <hi>Abſtinence from Meats,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4 1.</note> and <hi>to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Marriage;</hi> though he himſelf, and common experience tells us, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>it is much more convenient</hi> to be free, than bound in Wedlock, yet he calls that Doctrine, <hi>the Doctrine of Devils,</hi> and therefore I need not ſcruple to call it <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides theſe three, I do not remember that in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament I find any Tenet branded as Antichriſtian; for though there are many other things, as <hi>Free-will, Merit, Worſhip of Images, Not ſanctifying of the Lords day, or one day in ſeven;</hi> and the like, which are ſeverely condemned as Falſe and Impious; yet I call that only <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> which directly oppoſes Chriſt in ſome of his Offices, or in his Purchaſe and Acquiſition for believers.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for that which was to be the Doctrine of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Practice of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is recorded to diſcover it ſelf in theſe three things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Pride,</hi> whereby he oppoſes our Saviours <hi>Humility and ſelf-denial.</hi> For thus our Saviours ſtinting that Ambitious ſtrife of his Diſciples, concerning <hi>who ſhould be greateſt: The Rulers of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do exerciſe Lordſhip over them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20 25.</note> 
               <hi>but it ſhall not be ſo among you;</hi> but he that will be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>affect the Primacy amongſt you, let him be ſervant of all;</hi> and to enforce this, our Saviour urges his own Example, <hi>Even,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as the Son of man came not to be miniſtred unto, but to minister.</hi> And as for Power, ſo for Titles of Honour; our Saviour forbiding his Diſciples, to imitate the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were puffed up and ſwelled with thoſe Airy and Empty names of Honour amongſt men. <hi>Be not ye,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>called Doctor, or Maſter, or Father, or Teacher, i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.8.</note> Affect not to be ſo called, <hi>for you have one Teacher, which is Christ: Ye have one Father which is in Heaven; but all ye are Brethren.</hi> And therefore take heed leſt by taking upon you ſuch glorious ſtiles, you forget that Equality which ſhould be amongſt brethren. Thus <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But <hi>Antichrist</hi> thinks no Power too great, no Name too good for him:
<note place="margin">2 Theſ 2.4.</note> And therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gives this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of him that he is one <hi>who oppoſeth himſelf (i.e.</hi> againſt <hi>Christ) and exalts himſelf above all that is called God, or</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which word I take to ſignifie the <hi>Emperial ſtile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 25.21.</note> for the Emperour in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105048:16"/>Latine was called <hi>Augustus,</hi> in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, that Antichriſt ſhould advance himſelf above all <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Emperours) So that he ſhall ſit as a God, in the Temple of God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf that he is God; i. e.</hi> aſſuming unto himſelf the exerciſe of Divine Power and Honour, as if he were a God on Earth; which whoever doth muſt needs in that be <hi>Antichrist, i. e.</hi> oppoſe the Humility both practiſed and preſcribed by <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond thing, wherein the Practice of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was to diſcover it ſelf, is <hi>Pompe,</hi> as it is oppoſed to Chriſtian <hi>Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> I know very well that <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Riches</hi> are <hi>res mediae,</hi> that in themſelves neither ſtate doth make us more or leſs accepted to God: But yet ſuch hath been and is the Fate of true Religion, that <hi>Riches,</hi> moſt commonly, are the Portion of the men of this world, out of which Chriſtianity calls its followers but Diſgraces, Loſſes, and Poverty are moſt uſually the Attendants on ſtrictneſs and Holineſs: Thus our Saviour affirms the condition of <hi>Beaſts of the Earth,</hi> and <hi>Birds of the Heaven,</hi> to be, in outward reſpects, much better than his,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.20.</note> For <hi>the one,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have holes, the other have neſts, but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head:</hi> And thereupon cals his Followers <hi>to leave every thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14.26, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> to be in a readineſs to hazard all rather than to quit their profeſſion, or elſe <hi>they were not fit to be his Diſciples.</hi> But <hi>Antichrist,</hi> quite contrary, propoſes worldly wealth, and Temporal Rewards unto his Followers; and ſeeks to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile Piety and Preferment, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſelf-denial with that which doth directly contradict it. For which reaſon, I ſuppoſe, it is, that the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.16.</note> having premiſed that <hi>the Love of the World was Enmity unto God;</hi> for, <hi>whatever is in the World, the deſire of the Fleſh,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Pleaſure;) <hi>the deſire of the Eyes, (i. e.</hi> Riches;) <hi>and the pride of Life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 18.</note> (<hi>i. e.</hi> outward State and Magnificence,) <hi>they are not of God, but of the World.</hi> To which he immediately ſubjoyns, <hi>Little children, it is the laſt hour, and as you have heard, that Antichriſt ſhall come, ſo now there are many Antichriſts:</hi> Plainly intimating, that there were ſome, who, by immerſing themſelves in the Delights and Exceſſes of the World, did abundantly diſcover their <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> temper. And accordingly in the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 12.</note> that <hi>Woman,</hi> which figured the <hi>true Church,</hi> as ſo on as ever <hi>ſhe had brought forth, i. e.</hi> received and embraced the Faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhe is ſaid to flee <hi>into the Wilderneſs,</hi> where ſhe was to abide for a long time in a diſconſolate and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted condition; where it is obſervable, that the time, <hi>viz.</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105048:16"/>1260. daies, which is allotted unto the <hi>womans abode in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> is the very ſame time, in which the <hi>Witneſſes were to Prophecy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>being arrayed with ſackcloath;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 11.3.</note> to ſhew their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent and needy ſtate, as likewiſe the <hi>Temple,</hi> or true worſhippers <hi>of God, was ſo long to be trampled under food,</hi> which likewiſe is the time limited for Antichriſts Reign and Perſecution. Thus the <hi>true Church,</hi> like <hi>Chriſt</hi> her Head, finds no peace on Earth, but is fain to ſeek ſhelter in a <hi>Wilderneſs.</hi> But that <hi>woman,</hi> which is the Embleme of the <hi>Falſe Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 17 3.</note> is repreſented to ſit in goodly Array <hi>upon a ſcarlet-coloured Beaſt: And the woman was cloathed with Purple and Scarlet, and adorned with Gold, and precious Stones, and Pearls; i. e.</hi> Tricked up and ſet out with the utmoſt circumſtances of outward Glory and Magnificence, by which ſhe doth allure and entice her Followers; making her Religion as pompous, Theatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſpecious as may be, that ſo it might be taking. But we have not ſo learned <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was himſelf <hi>poor,</hi> and his Doctrine ſtrict and ſevere; ſo that to take off from the end of Religion, which is to withdraw men from Earth, that they may mind Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and to change the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> into the <hi>ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> and <hi>pompe</hi> of <hi>Service,</hi> this is not of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> therefore it is <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The third and laſt thing in the practice of <hi>Ancichriſt,</hi> by which he may be deſcried is <hi>Perſecution</hi> of all that diſſent from him, though never ſo holy or Religious otherwiſe; which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Note of Antichriſt, as being directly contrary to the <hi>Meekneſs, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> of our Saviour. For when the Diſciples deſired that they might call down for Fire from Heaven, to puniſh thoſe Barbarous and Inhumane <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who would not ſo much as allow him a lodging in one of their Villages;
<note place="margin">Luk. 9.55.</note> Our Saviour ſharply reproves them, <hi>Ye know not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of what ſpirit you are; i. e.</hi> the Chriſtian ſpirit is not a bloody, a ſelf-avenging: but a tender, a compaſſionate ſpirit; <hi>For the Son of man came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> And again,
<note place="margin">Ib. v. 50.</note> when ſome of his Diſciples told him, that they <hi>found ſome doing miracles in his name, but they forbade them;</hi> becauſe, ſay they, <hi>they followed not us. Forbid them not,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>for he that is not againſt us, is for us.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Let every man,</hi> ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> 
               <hi>be fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in his own mind, i. e.</hi> of the Neceſſity and Lawfulneſs of that which he doth; <note place="margin">16.</note>And <hi>judge not one another, but judg this rather, that none
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105048:17"/>do put a ſtumbling block, or a cauſe of offence before his Brother.</hi> And again,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>We,</hi> ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>do not Lord it over your Faith,</hi> or Conſciencious Perſwaſion in things indifferent; but <hi>if any be otherwiſe-minded God will reveal this to him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.15.</note> with many hundreds of Scriptures more to the ſame purpoſe, which ſhew, that nothing doth more ſavour of the ſpirit of Chriſtianity than Mutual For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance and Toleration. And that nothing is more repugnant to it, then Harſhneſs, Rigour, and Imperious Exaction. But <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> quite contrary, is all made up of cruelty and unmercifulneſs; <hi>The falſe Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>which come in my Name, they wear ſheeps-cloathing, but inwardly they are ravening Wolves; i.e.</hi> They ſeem mild and gentle, but indeed are Furious, and bloud-thirſty men; and therefore in the <hi>Revelation, Antichrist</hi> is compared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Beaſt <hi>which hath horns like a Lambe (i. e.</hi> in outward appearance ſeems to act for Chriſt) but <hi>ſpeaks like a Dragon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> in his Decrees and Impoſitions is Outragious and Bloudy; Inſomuch, <hi>that he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all, great and ſmall, rich and poor, free and bond, to receive a mark in their Foreheads, or in their hands; That no man might buy or ſell, ſave he that had that mark, i. e.</hi> They were either to joyn with him in his publike Worſhip, and by ſome outward Teſtimony manifeſt their Conformity, or elſe <hi>they ſhould not buy nor ſell, i.e.</hi> not ſo much as exerciſe any civill Commerce or Society with men: Nor is that all, that he will exclude ſuch from the benefits of Life, <hi>But,</hi> ſaith the Text,
<note place="margin">R. v. 18.13.</note> 
               <hi>if men will not worſhip the beaſt, and that Image which he hath ſet up,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he cauſes that they be ſlain;</hi> which is the utmoſt expreſſion of Inhumanity: and therefore among the Merchandize of the <hi>Falſe Church,</hi> here are reckoned, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the ſouls or lives of men,</hi> either beſtained and poyſoned with their Inventions, or deſtroyed by their Butchery. So infinitely dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent is <hi>Antichriſt</hi> from <hi>Chriſt. Chriſt</hi> would not have the leaſt of thoſe offended that believe on him; <hi>Antichriſt</hi> doth nothing elſe but offend them. And ſo much for the ſecond thing in our Saviours Prediction, <hi>viz.</hi> The way how <hi>Antichrist</hi> or the <hi>Falſe Prophet</hi> is to be deſtroyed; in the decyphering of which, I have purely followed that Method,
<note place="margin">Rev. 19 10.</note> which <hi>the Spirit of Propheſie,</hi> which is called <hi>the Teſtimony of Jeſus</hi> in Scripture, hath chalked out to me, without mingling the leaſt of my own Inventions and uncharitable Preſumptions with it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing obſervable in our Saviours Prediction, is <hi>the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105048:17"/>Time when Antichrist ſhould ariſe;</hi> which is implied in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>then,</hi> i. about the Time that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed; which that it was a very proper time for <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to ariſe in, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from theſe two Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe then the Apoſtles, and others, who planted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and were infallibly inſpired by God, were all dead; and therefore when theſe Suns were Set, it is no wonder if <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Night</hi> did ſpeedily overſpread the World. This is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimated by our Saviour, where he tells his Diſciples, that before <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed, <hi>They ſhall,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.9.11.</note> 
               <hi>deliver you up unto Tribulation, and they ſhall kill you;</hi> whereupon immediately he adds, <hi>And many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall deceive many.</hi> As when the Banks and Bounds are broken down, the River preſently doth overflow the Valleys, ſo when the Apoſtles were gone, who were to ſtand in the Breach, and to reſiſt the Torrent, Corruption and Will-worſhip did, like a deluge, over-run the World; as <hi>Hegeſippus, Euſebius,</hi> and other Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, do both mention and ſadly complain of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe I take the <hi>Spirit of Antichriſt,</hi> as I find it diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Scripture, to conſiſt in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. An ambitious affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Soveraignty or Dominion,</hi> or in a word, <hi>A Love of Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> This the Apoſtle cenſures in <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; i. e. <hi>He loved to be firſt or chief,</hi> and took upon him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>the ſole power to excommunicate.</hi> Now while <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was ſtanding in its glory, no Church could vye with that for ſuperiority, as being undoubtedly the <hi>Mother Church,</hi> from whence all the reſt did proceed: But as ſoon as ever the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>the Jewiſh ſtate</hi> was removed, then the biggeſt City laid claim to be the beſt Church, and never reſted till it had fixed in it ſelf a ſpiritual, as before it had done a temporal and earthly Dominion.</p>
            <p>I know very well that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>He which withholdeth,</hi> or <hi>bindeth, i.e.</hi> Keepeth <hi>Antichriſt</hi> from appearing, is commonly underſtood of the <hi>Civill Empire</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. c. 32. &amp; ad Scap. c. 2. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cr, adv. Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c 27.</note> ſo <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> in his <hi>Apology,</hi> and other of the Ancients; but for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reaſons I think it is rather to be meant of the <hi>Jewiſh State;</hi> as likewiſe, becauſe the Apoſtle in the ſame place ſaith, that the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity was then working;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaies,
<note place="margin">2 Joh. 2. &amp;c 4.</note> that <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105048:18"/>was then come;</hi> whereas there was no conſiderable change in the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> for ſome hundreds of years after. But <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed within few years after the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> Dearn, and he ſeems to intimate that he ſaw ſome evident Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promes of, and Preparations o it, even in his own name, in thoſe words of his,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The wrath, i. e.</hi> threatned by our Saviour, <hi>is come upon them to the uttermoſt.</hi> But <hi>John</hi> did ſurvive the ruine of that City, whereupon he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies, <hi>that Antichriſt was then come;</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mentioned by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> being in his time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
            <p>Having thus fixed the <hi>Riſe of Antichriſt</hi> upon the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> we muſt take notice that there is a threefold <hi>Epoche</hi> or account of time, from whence we may date the ruine of that City: The firſt was in the time of <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> about forty years after our Saviour, and then <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was working, being then in his ſeeds and beginnings. The ſecond was under <hi>Adrian,</hi> about 150 years after our Saviour; and then <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was come to ſome conſiſtence and maturity, for to paſs by the Falſe and Unſound Doctrines and corrupt Practices of that Age, as their enveighing againſt the <hi>Marriages,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>ſecond marriages of Miniſters;</hi> their <hi>Uſe of the Croſs,</hi> and counting it a kind of Charm; their <hi>voluntary Faſting and Penance,</hi> and placing ſome kind of holineſs in the unmarried ſtate, as may be ſeen at large in <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian,</hi> and others. But to paſs by theſe, about <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time it was,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> that <hi>Victor,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did take upon him to excommunicate all the <hi>Eaſtern Biſhops</hi> that did not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize <hi>Eaſter</hi> at the ſame time with him; by which Irregular and Preſumptuous Decree, he did not only take that for granted, which I think is very queſtionable, <hi>viz. the keeping of Eaſter,</hi> I mean upon a Religious account, but likewiſe he aſſumed a power which did not belong to him; and ſufficiently ſhews that that Church was then aiming at Empire and Rule rather than Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The third and laſt date of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Ruine was in <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's</hi> time, when the Temple was torne up by an Earthquake, and that Prophecy of our Saviour literally fulfilled, that <hi>there ſhould not be left there one ſtone upon another.</hi> And about this time, it would be endleſs to recount the infinite abuſes and errours which were not only crept into, but had credit and countenance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105048:18"/>in the Church. The <hi>Doctrine of Merit and Juſtification by Works; the Worſhip of Angels; the forbidding of Marriage,</hi> and <hi>Abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Meats,</hi> being publikely owned, and this laſt ſo rigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſſed, that <hi>Socrates,</hi> a learned and moderate Hiſtorian, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr.</hi> l. 5. c. 22.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They count,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Fornication and all uncleanneſs an indifferent and dispenſable fault;</hi> but <hi>about their Feaſt and Faſt daies, they contend as for their lives,</hi> he adds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quite perverting the Commands of God, and giving Laws unto themſelves.</hi> At the ſame time likewiſe were appeals made unto <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr.</hi> l. 2. c. 8. &amp;c. 17.</note> to <hi>Julius</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> there, as the <hi>Judge of Civil Controverſies;</hi> and a <hi>Decree</hi> either made or tacitly aſſented to, that <hi>no Act of a Council ſhould be valid at which the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>was not preſent;</hi> which ſhews that Antichriſt, <hi>i.e.</hi> that proud, aſpiring, overweening Spirit was well grown, and arrived almoſt to its full ſtature. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith my Author, i.e.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr.</hi> l. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>now of a long time had the Biſhoprick of Rome advanced it ſelf</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>beyond the Sacerdotal unto a Tyrannical Power, and therefore would not permit thoſe who were of the ſame Orthodox Faith with them to meet and aſſemble quietly in their Jurisdiction.</hi> And this was written by <hi>Socrates,</hi> before the ſtile of <hi>Univerſal Biſhop</hi> was yet thought of; which within a hundred years after was challenged, and then was the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> compleat and perfect.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt thing in our Saviours Prediction, is <hi>the way how Antichrist ſhould riſe, together with the Progreſs he ſhould make; They ſhall ſhew,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>great ſigns and wonders, to deceive, if it were poſſible, even the Elect.</hi> And this note either of pretending to, or really effecting of <hi>Miracles</hi> is mentioned both by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2 9.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of him, that <hi>his working is according to Satan, in all power and ſigns,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>lying wonders</hi> in this ſenſe, as if their <hi>Miracles</hi> were all <hi>forged</hi> and <hi>falſe,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wonders done in defence and maintenance of a lye, i. e.</hi> His Doctrine ſhould be ſo falſe, that it ſhould have nothing to uphold it but meerly the Reputation of Miracles, whether true or falſe. So the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith, that the Beaſt, who had <hi>horns like a Lambe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.13.</note> doth great miracles, <hi>ſo that he makes even fire to deſcend from Heaven;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105048:19"/>what he there cals a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> in another place he calls, <hi>the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet who does ſigns and wonders.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19.20.</note> So that our Saviour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles do both grant that Miracles may be done by a falſe Power; and likewiſe affirm, that whoever hath nothing elſe to alledge for his Religion, but meerly <hi>Miracles,</hi> that ſame is <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> For Truth ſtands not in need of ſuch outward Circumſtances to underprop it; and, according to the Scripture, <hi>Miracles</hi> are not to prove the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but the <hi>Doctrine</hi> is to prove the <hi>Miracles,</hi> whether they are from God or not. But yet, ſaith our Saviour, with thoſe Arts and waies he ſhall ſo far prevail, as even almoſt to ſtagger the belief <hi>of the very Elect; Many ſhall follow their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Doctrines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.2. Rev. 13.</note> ſaith <hi>Peter; the World ſhall wonder after the Beast,</hi> ſaith <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>he ſhall deceive the Inhabitants of the earth,</hi> &amp;c. all which places do note an almoſt Univerſal ſeducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And if any ask, how it comes to paſs that Corruption, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the received <hi>Tenets</hi> and <hi>Maximes</hi> of Chriſtianity ſhould be ſo generally embraced,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2 10, 11</note> the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath given it, <hi>Becauſe men have not received the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved, therefore ſhall God ſend upon them the ſtrong working of deceit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>that they ſhould believe a Lye, i.e.</hi> Men being unwilling to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to the guidance of Truth, which ſhines clearly by its own Light, both in Scriptures, and in their own Underſtandings; therefore ſhall God ſuffer them to be ſo brutiſh and Sottiſh, as to quit their Reaſon, and to be led up and down by any fond and ridiculous Errour, as thoſe Impoſtors ſhall guide them.</p>
            <p>I have done with the Prediction of our Saviour concerning <hi>Antichrist,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. <hi>Canenes. Concil. Trident.</hi>
               </note> and if upon your enquiry you find, that there is that <hi>Religion</hi> in the world which hath eſpouſed and embodied into their Confeſſion of Faith all the Opinions of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> If there be that <hi>Church</hi> in the world, which ſtill pretends to do, and, for ought I know, doth <hi>reall Miracles,</hi> upon which they bottome their Plea to be the <hi>true Church;</hi> if they maintain <hi>Perſecution, Violence,</hi> and <hi>Fraud;</hi> if they have diſpirited and diſenvigoured Religion by their worldly Pompe and Gallantry; and make thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in this world a ſign that God doth love and favour them, all which are <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Tenets and Practices. If there be that <hi>Perſon</hi> in the world, who hath aſſumed the very ſtile of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> who hath trampled upon <hi>Kings,</hi> and trode upon the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105048:19"/>Necks of <hi>Emperours;</hi> who in his <hi>Canon Law</hi> is called <hi>God;</hi> and, like God, doth diſpenſe with all, both Divine and Humane Laws; then firſt, certainly <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is already come; and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, is to deny as great evidence and notoriety of fact, as to deny it is day when the Sun ſhineth. And ſecondly, He which foretold that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould thus come, with all theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that I have ſummed up, he was undoubtedly a <hi>true Prophet, the true Meſſiah;</hi> for to repeat the Argument in my Text; He told us theſe <hi>things before they came to paſs,</hi> and <hi>we find that they are come to paſs;</hi> and <hi>therefore he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Uſe that I ſhall make of this whole Diſcourſe is:
<list>
                  <item>1. To <hi>convince the Unreſolved.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To <hi>confirm thoſe who are already ſetled.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1,</label> The firſt uſe ſhall be <hi>to convince the Unreſolved;</hi> I have already ſpoken ſomething to awaken thoſe that are reſolute and perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory <hi>Unbelievers;</hi> but there are many, who may be yet in their enquiring, doubting, and diſputing ſtate; who are not unwilling to embrace the Faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but they find it to be ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to every thing of natural Reaſon within them: and likely to be attended with ſo much hazard and danger, that they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſhamed or afraid to own it, but yet are not fixed in poſitive denial of it, but through uncertainty they are alwaies Anxious and wavering. Such as theſe ought to be tenderly and gently dealt with; and two things I ſhall propoſe to them, which may help to alleviate and to abate their Prejudices.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſtian Religion is in no part of it <hi>unreaſonable;</hi> for, ſince the Proof of it in general depends upon the cleareſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, <hi>viz. The fulfilling of Propheſies,</hi> then the belief of it muſt needs be rational. I know very well, that the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures, viz. <hi>The Incarnation of the Son of God, three Perſons of the Godhead, the Immediate Acting of the Holy Spirit upon the heart of Believers,</hi> and the like, are all <hi>Myſterious,</hi> and no waies reconcileable to <hi>Humane Apprehenſion;</hi> but then we muſt conſider, that theſe things are not propoſed to our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings to comprehend them; but meerly to our Faith to believe them; which where there is a firm and demonſtrable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105048:20"/>ground of <hi>Beliefe</hi> may be done, even to many things that we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not. And the great hindrance that hath kept <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> from entring into the minds of men, is want of attendance to that diſtinction, for many have both confounded themſelves, and ſubverted the Faith of others by preſſing upon them a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of what is no waies by us Intelligible. And therefore all thoſe <hi>Diſputes</hi> about <hi>Predeſtination, Trinity, Reſurrection, Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and the like, are for the greateſt part of them unprofitable and dangerous; becauſe they are not content barely to aſſert the Truth, (which is then beſt done when it is put into the plaineſt and moſt unſcholaſtick Language of Scripture) but our Arguers do over and above enquire <hi>de modo,</hi> and labour to give reaſons for thoſe ſtupendious and amazing Myſteries, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> cries out <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> upon, and, for the moſt part, ends the Diſpute with a Reproof of the Diſputer. And therefore ſuch of you as are not yet fixed in your belief; ſet your ſelves purely upon this Article, viz. <hi>to enquire whether Jeſus be the Chriſt;</hi> and never give it over till it hath pleaſed God fully to confirm you in it. And my Reaſons for this Advice are theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe this is the moſt effectual and ready way to prove unto you the <hi>Divine Authority of the Scriptures.</hi> Thoſe who ſet upon this work by endeavouring to prove the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be the <hi>Word of God,</hi> as they lye in groſs, and in their diffuſed Bulk, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding by <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>Verſe,</hi> do undertake a Tedious and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible Task; for there thoſe ordinary and trivial Objections of <hi>miſtakes,</hi> and <hi>variations in Copies, miſtranſlations,</hi> and the like, are never to be aſſoiled; but if you draw the ſeveral lines in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into their Center, and contract them into Chriſt, as you uſe to do the Sun-beams into a burning-glaſs, then do they caſt a quick and vigorous luſtre, ſufficient to enlighten and warm even the moſt ſtiffe and rigid Oppoſer. He that would demonſtrate the <hi>Providence of God,</hi> would not, I ſuppoſe, begin with the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutiae mundi, the leſſer things of the World,</hi> as Flies and Inſects, but he would fix, as <hi>David</hi> doth, upon the Sun, or ſome noble and conſpicuous part, whoſe Uſe is undeniable; and thence conclude, that if Providence hath a reſpect to any one part of the world, it cannot be imagined but it ſhould have an Influence over all; for elſe it muſt either be Finite or Partial, which is abſurd. So in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105048:20"/>aſſerting of Scriptures, begin with that which they all point at, and which if one place be queſtioned, thouſands of the ſame kind will evince, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Meſſiah was to come,</hi> which is the great deſign of the Old Teſtament. That <hi>the Meſſiah is come,</hi> which is the ſum of the New; and then all the other parts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture will be owned, as ſuited to the Divine and Heavenly Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> who took a body, not only that he might dye our Price, but that he might live our Pattern. And almoſt each Line of Scripture, eſpecially in the New Teſtament, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes either his Life, or his Language.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here the Doubter muſt begin, becauſe this is the readieſt way to aſcertain himſelf whether he be guided by <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> or not. So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>None can call Jeſus the Lord but by the Holy Spirit;</hi> and <hi>John,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.2.</note> Every Spirit that confeſſeth Jeſus the Meſſiah to be come in the fleſh, is of God.</hi> They do not mean, that ſaying this in words is a ſign of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> for what is more eaſie? but the owning it in heart, this whoever doth, may be ſure he hath the <hi>Spirit.</hi> And the reaſon is plain, becauſe where the Object propoſed doth exceed any natural power, there muſt be a new power given, by which that Object is to be received. Thus the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> argues concerning <hi>future glory, Hereafter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.3.</note> ſaith he, <hi>we ſhall be like him, i. e.</hi> Chriſt, <hi>becauſe we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> There will be a proportion and ſimilitude between Chriſts body and ours, becauſe our viſive Faculty ſhall be ſo exceedingly advanced, as that we ſhall be able to perceive him in his utmoſt radiance of Glory. So in belief, ſince the ſoul when it doth it, is heightned beyond any native Virtue of its own, it is a ſign that Gods Spirit hath illuminated and enlarged its Capacity. Thus the Apoſtle, <hi>We are ſaved by Grace through Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>and that not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God; i. e.</hi> that very Faith, by which we apprehend Chriſt, is as much the gift of God as Chriſt himſelf that is apprehended by it. I know very well this ſeems harſh to many who are willing to boaſt in themſelves; but if ever you come to believe indeed, you will find the Difficulties, your Natural Reaſon doth urge and vex you with, to be inſuperable, untill the Spirit of God, by infuſing new light, doth explain and ſolve them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Begin with enquiring whether <hi>Jeſus</hi> be the <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105048:21"/>becauſe upon this depends the whole courſe of your future Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Our Saviour required no more of any that came unto him, but <hi>to believe that he was the Son of God;</hi> not that he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude good works, but he knew that this was the only way to facilitate and expedite them. All the while we are either uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that our paſt ſins are pardoned, or our preſent ſervices ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; how lamely, how untowardly do we ſet about our duty? But when once we believe on <hi>Chriſt</hi> all that care is over, and the firmer our Faith is, the higher and more ardent will our Love be; which, like a flame, ſhoots through the ſoul, and carries it out with an heavenly quickneſs and ardency. Therefore, ſaith the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>If thou confeſs with thy mouth, that Jeſus is the Lord, i.e.</hi> If thou obeyeſt him) <hi>and believeſt in thy heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, (i.e.</hi> that he is the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> of which his Reſurrection is an infallible proof,) <hi>thou ſhalt be ſaved. For with the heart men believe unto righteouſneſs; (i.e.</hi> unto the juſtification of their Perſons,) <hi>and with the mouth is confeſſion made unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> But to think of making confeſſion, or doing any act of Religion, without Faith (deſire at leaſt, and the deſire of Faith is Faith) this is only to mock God, and to undo our ſelves by our fooliſh and hypocritical preſumptions, in preſenting unto him a Sacrifice which he abhors; For without <hi>Faith, i. e.</hi> reliance upon him for mercy, and out of Chriſt, God is nothing elſe but Juſtice, <hi>it is impoſſible to pleaſe him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Doubter hath gone thus far, as to find that if he will be ſatisfied, here he muſt begin; his next courſe will be to run over in his mind thoſe Arguments which our Saviour uſeth to evince his being the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> ſuch are the <hi>heavenlineſs of his Language;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8.43.</note> 
               <hi>Why do you not,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>know my ſpeech? i.e.</hi> Why do you not perceive, even by my manner of diſcourſe that I am come from heaven, full of that God in whoſe Name I ſpeak?
<note place="margin">Joh. 10.21.</note> For, as ſome of the Jews ſaid, <hi>theſe are not the words of him that hath a devil:</hi> Theſe are not the words of one that came to deceive the world, and to boaſt of himſelf to be that which he was not. Another Argument our Saviour urges, is the holineſs of his Life;
<note place="margin">Joh 8.46. Joh. 10.32.</note> 
               <hi>Which of you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth convince me of ſin?</hi> and <hi>many good works have I done amongſt you, for which of them do you ſtone me?</hi> An holy, humble, ſelf-denying man, who forbad even
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105048:21"/>his Miracles to be publiſhed, cannot, without intolerable malice, be ſuppoſed to aſſume a title which did not belong to him. Add to this the God-like Patience and Reſolution of his Death, dying in defence of this very Tenet; unprovoked with injuries, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out his ſoul in charity to men, <hi>Father forgive them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23.34.</note> 
               <hi>for they know not what they do;</hi> at the ſame time both praying and pleading for his bittereſt Enemies; and then giving up himſelf unto his Father with perfect Affiance. <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. v. 46.</note> 
               <hi>into thy hands do I commend my Spirit.</hi> Add yet farther, the Teſtimony of his Followers, who ſaw him after he was riſen; the ſucceſs of his Doctrine in ſpite of Perſecution; and above all, the fulfilling of Propheſies, as I have already mentioned; Truly then if he that doubted be not ſatisfied; if he that was <hi>almoſt,</hi> doth not become <hi>altogether</hi> a Chriſtian, he is ſtrangely wanting to himſelf, for God is not wanting to aſſiſt thoſe who do but begin to enquire after him: every doubt that ariſeth being nothing elſe but a Motion of Gods Spirit, whereby he would draw us unto himſelf.</p>
            <p>Having thus cleared, that to believe is not unreaſonable, as the Unbeliever ſuppoſeth; the next thing I ſhall propoſe is this: That</p>
            <p n="2">2. To <hi>obey</hi> is not dangerous; for though we may <hi>loſe our Lives,</hi> yet ſure we ſhall be ſufficient gainers if we <hi>ſave our ſouls.</hi> And therefore let the Doubter ſtrengthen himſelf with repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Heaven in its fulneſs of Joy alwaies before his eyes. That Doctrine which teacheth, that we are <hi>not to have an eye to the recompence of reward,</hi> it is falſe and dangerous; It is falſe, becauſe it contradicts the Command and the Example of Chriſt, who <hi>for the joy that was ſet before him despiſed the Croſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb 12.2.</note> Thus <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> thus <hi>Paul</hi> did both eye the Reward themſelves, and enjoyn it as a duty upon others. 2. It is dangerous, firſt, becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets infinite ſcruples, eſpecially in young Converts, whoſe firſt inducement muſt either be from their hopes, or their Feares, and which way ſoever they begin they have our Saviour ſometime uſing Threats, otherwhiles mingling Promiſes, to juſtifie their being wrought upon by either. 2. It makes the greateſt and moſt comfortable part of the Word uſeleſs, and that is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; and if men may live above the Promiſes, it will quickly follow, that they may live above the Precepts too; and what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105048:22"/>the end of ſuch Doctrine may be, is too apparent. I ſay therefore to the yet Doubting Chriſtian, fetch new ſtrength &amp; vigour from the Promiſes; for if thy Belief be Reaſonable, I am ſure thy Obedience, though it brings ſuffering, is highly ſo; for no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany preſſure,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> how grievous ſoever, can countervaile that full and everlaſting weight of happineſs which is laid up for Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Obeyers of the Goſpel. And that is a Theme ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, that I need not inſiſt upon it.</p>
            <p>So much for the firſt Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond Uſe is to confirm and ſtrengthen Believers: <hi>He that ſtandeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12:</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, and Faith only is the cauſe of a Chriſtians ſtanding, <hi>let him take heed lest he fall; And take heed,</hi> ſaith he to the believing Hebrews,
<note place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>lest there be in any of you an evill heart of unbelief, to Apoſtatize from the living God.</hi> Nothing doth undo the greateſt part of Chriſtians, but their Confidence; whereby, preſuming upon their preſent ſtock of Faith, they lay in no freſh recruits, and ſo fall, if not finally, (for that no <hi>elect Perſon</hi> can do) yet foully, as <hi>Peter</hi> did: whoſe ſecurity betrayed him into that which coſt him many bitter Tears. This kind of <hi>Bread</hi> is to be begged and received new every day from Heaven, or elſe we have no certainty that it will continue with us one moment. And therefore whatever we do, let us take care that <hi>our Faith fail not;</hi> a breach there, is like a wound in the head, for the moſt part mortall; and if at any time there have been Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Interciſions made in that Grace, repair them preſently by quickning and feeding your Faith with new Arguments; New, if not for Subject and Matter, yet for Light and for Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. Now this often reflecting upon our Saviours Prediction, is the beſt expedient you can provide: For that was it which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the Apoſtles, who were of as ſlow, incredulous, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie a temper to believe as any of us can be; when our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had told the Jews,
<note place="margin">Joh. 2.22.</note> that <hi>in three daies he would deſtroy the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and raiſe it up again,</hi> meaning the Temple of his Body; The Evangeliſt <hi>John</hi> obſerves, That <hi>when he was raiſed from the dead, his Diſciples remembred, that he had ſaid this unto them; and,</hi> he adds, <hi>they believed the Scripture,</hi> (which foretold this of the <hi>Meſſiah) and the word which Jeſus had ſaid;</hi> (who foretold it of himſelf,) where he makes our Saviours foretelling his own <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105048:22"/>be a <hi>medium</hi> by which the Diſciples did ſtrengthen their Faith, even after they had ſeen him riſen. And when they ran to the Sepulchre in the midſt of their Deſpairs and Fears, as now ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that their Maſter was utterly gone, and all their Faith ungrounded; the Angels tell them, <hi>Remember,</hi> ſay they, <hi>how he ſpake unto you, while he was yet in Galilee, ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 24.8.</note> 
               <hi>the Son of man muſt be delivered into the hands of ſinful men, and be crucified, and be raiſed again the third day.</hi> And, ſaies the Evangeliſt, <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred his words; i.e.</hi> Reflecting upon them, which their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſorrow and impatience made them to forget, they did a little moderate and appeaſe their ſorrow. By the example then of thoſe Apoſtles, often mind your ſelves of our Saviours Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and they will be of great advantage and comfort to you in theſe three Caſes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In caſe of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> which are already come.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In caſe of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> which may come.</p>
            <p n="3">III. In caſe of <hi>Future Glory,</hi> which though it be now delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet we have a promiſe that it will come.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The reflecting upon our Saviours Predictions will be of great uſe to comfort Believers, in reſpect of the <hi>Hereſies</hi> which already are come; I know it is a ſad and troubleſome thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a true Chriſtian to ſee the Diviſions and Contentions of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;</hi> to have the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church diſturbed by <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and the Unity of Faith divided by <hi>Errour;</hi> but as our Saviour ſaid to his Diſciples concerning the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>When you ſee Wars, and Tumults, be not troubled, for all theſe things muſt come to paſs.</hi> So ſay I, when you ſee <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Errour</hi> ſpreading it ſelf, and Parties, and ſidings, under pretence of advancing Truth, miſcalling <hi>Faction</hi> by the name of Religion; be not ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, for we know who hath told us, That <hi>there muſt be Hereſies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>thoſe whoſe Faith is approved or tried may be made manifeſt.</hi> As miſts and vapours ſerve to ſet out the Sun, ſo do Errours in ſome make the Truth that is owned by others more conſpicuous and apparent. I know the common cry of Ignorant or ſelf-deſigning men, is <hi>Put down Preaching, keep the People from reading the Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c. which is all one as if they ſhould ſay,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105048:23"/>Pull down the Sun, that we may prevent the riſing of Clouds and Mereors; The Scripture is like the Sun, and where it ſhines vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly, the dull Earth, <hi>i.e.</hi> Natural Ignorance in men, which conceives and apprehends it not, muſt needs ſend forth miſts and vapours. But, God forbid that the <hi>Children</hi> ſhould be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their <hi>Bread,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Dogs</hi> are ready to ſnatch it from them, and abuſe it. To Impriſon the Scripture in a dark and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Language, is indeed the ready way to prevent Hereſies, for what people cannot know they will be ſure not to contend about: So to extinguiſh the Sun, is the ready way to hinder Clouds, but then we ſhall be encompaſſed with the Horrour of Eternal Night: And to put out the Candle, that ſo all colours may agree in the dark, is a device as Politick as the devil himſelf that invented it, whoſe kingdom cannot ſubſiſt, unleſs the World do lull themſelves aſleep into a dull, ſtupid, irremediable Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. When the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi> is gone, I am afraid the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> will go with it; And I am ſure the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Reaſon</hi> leads us to nothing, but to <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> or to worſe, to <hi>ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> and <hi>impertinent ſuperstition, i.e.</hi> it makes us either ſo cunning, as to deceive others; or ſo fooliſh, as to be willing to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our ſelves. Therefore inſtead of ſuch diſmal contrivances, let <hi>Hereſies</hi> be ſuppreſſed by the ſame way by which they were raiſed, and that is by <hi>Preaching;</hi> and in the mean while, let not the Believer be troubled that many Errours are commonly ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted now, for he underſtood not the Nature of his Religion, nor the vain-glorious and yet fooliſh Pride of man, if he did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect them. For the Scripture is difficult, exceeding difficult and hard to be underſtood; and man is fooliſh, and ſo apt to miſtake; Proud, and ſo apt to preſume; Vain-glorious, and ſo apt to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his Conceits; which in the end prove <hi>Hereſies.</hi> But convince men once that it is their duty to be Humble, then they will ceaſe to vent; that they are to be charitable, and they will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to contend for their ſingular Fancies; and unto this Poſture of mind nothing but the bleſſing of God upon Preaching can bring them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This likewiſe will comfort Believers in reſpect of <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions</hi> which may come. That the Church of Chriſt is a Ship which doth beſt in a Storm, and that Faith muſt, like Gold, be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105048:23"/>tried in the Fire, is ſo known a thing that I need not inſiſt upon it. All that I infer is, that the having Afflictions foretold ſhould keep us from grieving at them when they do come. <hi>They,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 16.1.</note> ſaith our Saviour to his Diſciples, <hi>ſhall put you out of the Synagogues, and when they kill you, think they do God good ſervice. And I tell you theſe things, that you might not be offended, but remember that I told you of them.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man be moved by his Afflictions, for ye know that we are appointed unto this; And even when we were with you, we told you before that we ſhould be afflicted, even as alſo it is come to paſs.</hi> Thoſe who are forewarned of approaching Evils, are uſually armed againſt them: And therefore I have often wondred at that timid and abject Spirit which is in many under their Afflictions; which is a certain ſign that their <hi>Fear</hi> is above their <hi>Faith,</hi> and that they inwardly diſtruſt their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or doubt of their Reward. <hi>If ye are reproached,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, for the ſake of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 4.14. 2 Tim. 1.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>happy are ye, for the Spirit of Glory and of God reſts upon you.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy, We have not received the ſpirit of Fear, but the ſpirit of Power, therefore be not aſhamed of the Teſtimony of Chriſt.</hi> So that I conceive no condition is more joyous to a true Chriſtian, than to be endued with courage to ſuffer; for as in Winter the Fire doth redouble its hear, ſo God at that time of trial doth poure into the ſoul a more abundant ſupply of Comfort. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he that ſuffers is on the ſurer ſide. For though one may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and yet not be in the Right, yet he that perſecutes is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the wrong, as doing a thing which he hath no warrant for. So that as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> adviſeth,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>Let them who ſuffer according unto the Will of God,</hi> not be ſolicitous about the Event, but, go on in their Duty, though the World frown, <hi>and commit their ſouls unto him, in well-doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, The reflecting upon our Saviours Predictions, and the fulfilling of them, will be a great Comfort unto Believers, in reſpect of <hi>Future Glory,</hi> which is yet delayed, but will certainly come. I make no doubt, but every ſerious reſolved Chriſtian doth often wiſh with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, To be diſſolved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and to be with Chriſt;</hi> which certainly is a condition much better than to ſtruggle with the difficulties and uncertainties of Life, or to be clogged with a decaying, ſinful, and enticing body of Fleſh.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105048:24"/>
               <hi>We that are in this Tabernacle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>do groan being burdened;</hi> we would fain be ſtripped and diſrobed of this Cleg of Fleſh, and be put into preſent poſſeſſion of our Inheritance. But as Heirs muſt wait patiently, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>untill the time appointed by their Father,</hi> ſo muſt we. <hi>Let us hold faſt,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>the Profeſſion of our Faith without wavering, for he is faithful that hath promiſed; i.e.</hi> God will be as good as his word, and he hath ſhewn it, by fulfilling ſo many things already. So that,
<note place="margin">Ib. v. 36, 37.</note> as he adds, <hi>Ye have need of Patience, that when we have finiſhed the will of God, we may receive the Promiſe, For yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi> Life it ſelf is but of a very ſhort date, ſtretched out to its utmoſt ſpan; but what a nothing is it, if compared to Eternity? And cannot we wait ſome few years to do our Maſters buſineſs on Earth, but we muſt cry out for our wages before we have done our work? And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Unbelief</hi> is ready to creep in, and to make that Objection which ſome in <hi>Peter</hi> do,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Where is the Promiſe of his coming?</hi> Why doth Chriſt ſeem to neglect his Church, as if he had no regard unto his Vineyard? If theſe thoughts ariſe, as do what we can, come they will,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 39.</note> ſilence them with that of <hi>Peter, God is not ſlack concerning his Promiſe, as ſome men count ſlackneſs, but he is long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering towards us, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come unto the knowledge of the truth.</hi> God hath yet ſome Jewels to gather out of the Worlds Rubbiſh, and it is for their ſakes that the preſent frame of things is ſo long continued; for when their Number is accompliſhed, the Heaven ſhall be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up, as a Scroull, and the Earth ſhall be removed as an uſeleſs Scene. Wherefore, that I may conclude in the Apoſtle <hi>Peters</hi> words,
<note place="margin">Ibid. v. 18.</note> Believers, <hi>Ye knowing theſe things before, beware that ye be not led away by the ſeduction of ungodly men, and ſo fall from your own ſtedfastneſs; but grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. To whom be glory now and for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105048:24"/>
            <head>The Reſurrection of the Body Aſſerted and Cleared.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACT. 26.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpoken by way of Apology, in defence of himſelf, and of that moſt queſtioned and contradicted part of his Doctrine, <hi>viz. the Reſurrection of the Dead.</hi> This being in it ſelf, &amp; ſo accounted by him, the chief Foundation of a Chriſtians Hope, where ever that great Apoſtle came, he firſt laies, and then builds upon it. At <hi>Athens,</hi> among the learned Greeks,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.18.</note> we find him, by their own confeſſion, preaching but two things, <hi>Jeſus, and the Reſurrection.</hi> Afterwards, when he was empleaded by the Jews, he doth openly avow his Faith. <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee; i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 23.6.</note> I do with them hold and maintain the Reſurrection of the dead, for, as it follows, <hi>of the hope and reſurrection of the dead I am called in queſtion.</hi> Again, when he was convened before <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix,</hi> the Roman Deputy, he inſiſts upon the ſame Argument;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105048:25"/>for whereas he was charged by <hi>Tertullus</hi> with being an <hi>Heretick</hi> (which word is ſtill continued,
<note place="margin">Act. 24.5.</note> as that name of Obloquy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men are wont to diſgrace all new Diſcoveries of old Truths) <hi>Paul</hi> doth, in deſpight of that opprobrious Name, own that, which they called <hi>Hereſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 14.</note> and aloud proclaimes, that <hi>he believed,</hi> as all the Jews either did, or elſe had reaſon to do from their writings, <hi>there ſhould be a Reſurrection of the dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 15.</note> 
               <hi>both of the juſt and of the unjust.</hi> And now again, being brought forth before a mixt Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> he doth not only aſſert the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but likewiſe in theſe words offers to diſpute the Caſe, and to prove the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> by the dint of Reaſon.</p>
            <p>The words themſelves, which are propoſed by way of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contain three parts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Propoſition: that <hi>God will raiſe the Dead;</hi> for theſe words, <hi>Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</hi> Imply, that God will certainly raiſe them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An Oppoſition: that this is judged very incredible; for theſe words, <hi>Why is it</hi> judged incredible with you, <hi>that God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</hi> Implies, that this is ordinarily eſteemed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted as a thing incredible.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Demonſtration or a Conviction; that though this was judged incredible, yet indeed in it ſelf it was not ſo. For this queſtion, <hi>Why is it judged incredible,</hi> &amp;c. implies, that in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Queſtioner, there was no ſufficient Reaſon why it ſhould be ſo eſteemed.</p>
            <p>And theſe three Parts afford us three Doctrinal Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God will raiſe the Dead.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Doctrine, concerning the Reſurrection of the Dead, ſeems to natural men very incredible and very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Reſurrection of the Dead, however it be judged incredible by natural men, yet is in it ſelf highly credible, highly rational.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> The firſt Concluſion is, That God will raiſe the Dead; By <hi>Dead,</hi> here I mean that part of man which dies, <hi>viz.</hi> his Body; for the ſoul dies not, but when the body returns to its duſt, <hi>the ſoul
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105048:25"/>returns to him that gave it.</hi> And <hi>fear not them,</hi> ſaith our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7. Mat. 10.28.</note> 
               <hi>which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoul;</hi> with this part of our ſelves, as ſoon as ever we diſlodge from the Body, in the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> Language, we do <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i.e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>dwell and cohabite with the Lord,</hi> as in our proper Fathers houſe; for Heaven is the Souls Native and Original home: and therefore the re-union of that at laſt with the Body, is rather a return than a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. To ſpeak properly, the Body only riſes; thus our Saviour: <hi>The hour is coming,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.25.</note> 
               <hi>when the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God, and they who hear, ſhall live;</hi> where, that we might not be miſtaken, who he meant by dead, he adds by way of Explication, <hi>the houre is coming, when all who are,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 28.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the <hi>Tombes</hi> or <hi>Monuments, ſhall hear his voice.</hi> Now what elſe are <hi>Monuments</hi> but as one calls them,
<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> 
               <hi>Cadaverum ſtabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la; The ſtalls or receptacles of our corrupt and periſhing bodies.</hi> And therefore, when our Saviour envites all to come unto him, he uſes this by way of motive, that whoever came to him, he would not loſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>any thing that belonged to him,</hi> For, ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.39.</note> 
               <hi>I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> And again, <hi>He that believes on the Son, he ſhall have Eternal Life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> Implying, not only that if the body were not raiſed, ſomething which did eſſentially belong to man would be loſt and periſh; but likewiſe that without this raiſing of the body, Eternal Life would not be a ſtate of happineſs; becauſe it would be nothing elſe but an Eternal ſeparation from that part unto which the ſoul alwaies deſires to be joyned, and from which it is unwillingly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, as the Apoſtle argues, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. and following verſes.</p>
            <p>But doth our Saviour, do his Apoſtles ſay this only? Say not the Prophets the ſame? Is not this Article of our Faith, as well as all the reſt, to be proved out of the Old Teſtament?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Volkol.</hi> l. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> It will concern us a little to enquire into it, that we may ſtop thoſe mens mouths, who traduce our Religion, when they tell us, that it is wholly new; for if our Saviour had taught any thing which was either contrary to, or not eminently contained in the Writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the Jews would have had juſter Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to disbelieve his Doctrine than as yet they can pretend. For to inſiſt only upon this of the Reſurrection (which of all other Divine Diſcoveries ſeems to have leaſt footing in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.) It is plain that the Sadduces, who denied the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105048:26"/>are charged by our Saviour with Ignorance of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Ye erre,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not knowing the Scriptures; i. e.</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon thoſe places of Scripture wherein the Reſurrection is, though not directly ſpoken of, yet, plainly and by good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence implied. And thereupon he interprets one place, which, though not minded by them, yet, did verifie his Aſſertion. The Place is,
<note place="margin">Exod 3.</note> that ſtile which God, in his Apparition to <hi>Moſes,</hi> did aſſume,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22 31, 32.</note> when he calls himſelf, <hi>The God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob; this, ſaith our Saviour, doth demonſtrate the Reſurrection, <hi>For God is not God of the dead, but of the living;</hi> which words conclude two things: 1. That the fouls of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were then living with God. 2. That the living of their ſouls did neceſſarily infer that their bodies ſhould live too; ſince God is not God of this or that part only, but of the whole man. Another place in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament which did imply the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> is the promiſe God made to <hi>Abraham;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note> that <hi>he would bring him to a Land flowing with Milk and Honey.</hi> But by this <hi>Land,</hi> as the Apoſtle excellently argues,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.8, 16.</note> was not meant <hi>Canaan,</hi> for there <hi>Abraham</hi> had no poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but confeſſed of himſelf that he was a <hi>Pilgrim and ſtranger in it;</hi> which manifeſtly ſhews, that he deſired a Country, not that which he left, but a better, even a heavenly one; and that he looked after it, as a Place of Happineſs not only for his Soul, but likewiſe for his Body, is plain from what the Apoſtle ſaith afterwards, concerning the undaunted Conſtancy of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Martyrs, i.e.</hi> ſuch as died in bearing their witneſs for the Truths of God, before the coming of our Saviour in the fleſh. <hi>They would not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 35.</note> ſaith he, <hi>accept of deliverance, that they might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a better Reſurrection.</hi> Beſides theſe places which do imply this Doctrine, there are ſome that do expreſly mention it; As that of <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 19. Ver. 25.</note> whoſe words, however controverted by many Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, yet out of the Original, are exactly thus, <hi>For I know that my Redeemer (i.e.</hi> promiſed Meſſiah, unto whom this Term of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is moſt ordinarily applied, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>the Redeemer ſhall come to Sion, and unto them that turn from tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Jacob,</hi> which no Interpreter but muſt needs underſtand of the promiſed Saviour) <hi>liveth, and at laſt he ſhall ariſe</hi> (or <hi>ſtand, i.e.</hi> as Judge) <hi>over the Duſt, (i.e.</hi> either <hi>upon Earth,</hi> as our Engliſh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105048:26"/>Tranſlation hath it; or, <hi>over all men,
<note place="margin">Ver. 26.</note> though now for the preſent they lye in the duſt.</hi>) And, <hi>after my skin, when they (i.e.</hi> the worms, or the diſeaſes he was then afflicted with) <hi>have pierced through this (i.e.</hi> body of mine) <hi>yet out of my fleſh ſhall I ſee Jehovah, whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and my eyes ſhall behold,
<note place="margin">Ver. 27.</note> and not a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> which doth ſo clearly manifeſt his belief of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that, as the words cannot poſſibly be made ſenſe without it, ſo the Greek Tranſlation, by uſing the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, <hi>To raiſe up again to life,</hi> in that ſenſe I ſpeak of, doth plainly favour it. This likewiſe was the Faith of <hi>David,</hi> where he ſaies, <hi>Thou wilt not ſuffer thy Holy one to ſee Corruption:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11. Act. 3.</note> For though (as to the Riſing on the third day, <hi>i. e.</hi> before the natural Humours were reſolved and Corrupted) it was literally fulfilled by our Saviour, and ſo applied to him both by <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> yet it is plain, that he who ſpake thoſe words did likewiſe believe a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of his own Perſon, therefore he ſaies, <hi>My fleſh ſhall reſt in hope.</hi> But moſt plain is that of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who,
<note place="margin">Dan 12.2.</note> ſpeaking of <hi>Michael, i.e.</hi> Meſſiah <hi>the Prince,</hi> (and we know it was the Charge againſt our Saviour, that he made himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i.e. Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah the Prince</hi>) ſaies, that in his time, <hi>Many (i. e.</hi> the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) <hi>of them that ſleep in the duſt ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and everlaſting contempt;</hi> which is ſo clear a Prophecy of the Future Reſurrection, and in ſo expreſs Terms, that our Saviour in his Declaration of it ſeems to allude to theſe very words of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and to have had them in his eye; only what <hi>Daniel</hi> calls <hi>everlaſting contempt,</hi> our Saviour explains, by calling it, <hi>the Reſurrection of Condemnation: And thoſe,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>who do good, ſhall go forth to the Reſurrection of life; but thoſe who do evil, to the Reſurrection of Condemnation.</hi> So that from hence it evidently appears, that we Chriſtians, in this particular, do own no more than what other holy men among the Jews did before us; and our Apoſtle did very well underſtand what he ſaid, when in the words foregoing my Text, he tells them, that <hi>he was then judged for the Promiſe (i. e.</hi> of Future life and happineſs not to be attained, but after the Reſurrection) <hi>made by God unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> whereupon he proceeds to make that query, <hi>Why ſhould it be judged incredible, that God ſhould raiſe the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much for the firſt Obſervation.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105048:27"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Obſervation is this, That the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, though plainly revealed in Scripture, ſeems to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men very incredible;
<note place="margin">Act. 17.18.</note> ſo it appeared to the Learned Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers at <hi>Athens,</hi> who called <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Prater,</hi> or <hi>Trifler</hi> for preaching it: And they did ſo little underſtand what the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> meant, that they took it to be the name of ſome <hi>Daemon;</hi> for thus ſome ſaid of <hi>Paul, That he was a publiſher of ſtrange Daemons, becauſe he preached unto them Jeſus and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection;</hi> which laſt word ſhould have been left untranſlated, for they took <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake ſo much of, to be the name of ſome <hi>New Goddeſs.</hi> So likewiſe in this Chapter, when <hi>Paul</hi> makes a Relation of his Converſion, which yet was very mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, <hi>Feſtus</hi> heard him patiently, but when once he began to mention how Chriſt was raiſed from the dead,
<note place="margin">Act. 26.23, 24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Feſtus</hi> could hold no longer, but cryed out with a great deal of impatience, <hi>Paul thou art mad, too much learning</hi> hath quite unhinged thy braine, and <hi>overturned</hi> thee into madneſs.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 15.</note> Hence the Apoſtle, in that Chapter where he doth moſt elegantly diſpute it, brings in an heathen asking this queſtion,
<note place="margin">Ver. 35.</note> 
               <hi>But ſome man will ſay, How are the dead raiſed up?</hi> Which is not an <hi>How</hi> of enquiry, into the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Method of the Reſurrection, in what order it ſhall be accompliſhed; but an <hi>How</hi> of doubting, concerning the whole thing:
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.9.</note> Like <hi>Nicodemus</hi>'s How, <hi>How can theſe things be?</hi> And therefore in the Primitive Perſecutions, the enemies of Gods People never ſhewed more witty cruelty in any thing than in deviſing waies how to elude the Reſurrection; and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by mangling, torturing, and burning their bodies, but by ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering their Aſhes in the Rivers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſeb.</hi> l. 5. c. 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith mine Author, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>As if they had been able to conquer God, and deprive the Saints of their Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> Neither was this only the perſwaſion of the Heathen world, but we ſee oftentimes in Scripture, thoſe who owned higher Principles, yet manifeſting their doubts and deſpaires of this.
<note place="margin">c. 7.9.</note> Thus <hi>Job,</hi> notwithſtanding his ſo excellent confeſſion, in a fit of impatience cries out, As the cloud is conſumed and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away,
<note place="margin">c. 14.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſo he that goeth down to the grave ſhall come up no more.</hi> And again, <hi>There is hope,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of a tree, if it be cut down, that it will ſprout again, and that the tender branch thereof will not ceaſe.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105048:27"/>But, if a man dye, ſhall he live again?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 14.</note> By which words he ſeems to conclude, that by death at leaſt the Body is utterly loſt. So <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> when God, to try his faith, asked him this queſtion,
<note place="margin">c. 37.3.</note> 
               <hi>Son of man, can theſe bones live?</hi> That holy man durſt not affirm it, but uſes an anſwer which ſhews that he was altogether uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and at a loſs about it: <hi>O Lord God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou knoweſt; i.e.</hi> I am not able to reſolve thee; that <hi>dry bones ſhould live,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs as much to a Divine knowledge to comprehend, as to a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power to effect it. Thus in the New Teſtament the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, though they knew their Maſter to be the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and <hi>the Meſſiah,</hi> (which was a great maſter-piece of Faith) yet they did not at all underſtand the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> for when our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our after his Transfiguration did charge them, that they ſhould not tell any what they had ſeen, untill the Son of man were riſen from the dead; The Evangeliſt adds, that they kept the matter private to themſelves, but queſtioned or diſputed with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>what the riſing from the dead ſhould mean:</hi> at which time, it ſeems, they were ſo utterly ignorant of the thing, that they ſcarce underſtood the meaning of the word. Hence was it, that even then when the Reſurrection of our Saviour had cleared the Point,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.12.</note> and left ſcarce room for the leaſt umbrage of ſuſpition to enter; yet there were ſome in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> who ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denied it; and other,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.18.</note> of the <hi>Sect</hi> of <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> and <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who affirmed, <hi>that it was paſt already;</hi> So hard a matter was it for this Doctrine to get ground in the world;
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 13.6.</note> and therefore the Apoſtle when he ſums up the <hi>Myſtery of Godlineſs, i.e.</hi> as it is revealed by our Saviour, he makes this to be one great part of it, that <hi>Chriſt was</hi> not only <hi>riſen from the dead,</hi> but <hi>believed on in the World.</hi> The ſubduing of the world unto the perſwaſion and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our Saviours Reſurrection being every whit as miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as the raiſing him.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons why this appears ſo to incredible, to natural men, are</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe naturally men do doubt the Immortality of the Soul. I know very well, that there are many excellent Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes about this in the Heathen Writers; and <hi>Plato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phade.</note> in a certain Dialogue of his, brings in his Maſter <hi>Socrates,</hi> diſputing about it, with as much ſtrength of Reaſon, and clearneſs of Expreſſion, as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105048:28"/>the wit of man can poſſibly invent; but after all his fine ſayings he concludes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>But expreſly to affirm, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is indeed ſo, as I have diſcourſed of, doth by no means become an underſtanding man.</hi> And ſo makes it at the beſt only a probable opinion, without daring to think, as our modern Demonſtrators do, that he had fully and ſatisfactorily cleared it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſo much magnified <hi>Socrates,</hi> when he was now to be led unto execution, takes his farewell of the Judges in theſe words, which diſcover nothing but his uncertainty,
<note place="margin">Apol.</note> 
               <hi>I go to dye, and you to live, and which of us do go unto the best eſtate,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">De Senect.</note> 
               <hi>none knows but God alone.</hi> So <hi>Tully,</hi> the moſt Learned of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, calls <hi>Immortality</hi> an <hi>Errour, which he will by no means part with, becauſe he is pleaſed and delighted with it.</hi> Wherein he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers his Wiſhes,
<note place="margin">De Animâ.</note> rather than his Hopes; For as <hi>Tertullian</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently argues, to ſuppoſe the ſoul Immortal, it was in the Heathen nothing elſe but a bold and vain preſumption, ſince it alwaies lay in his power to deſtroy the Soule, who made it; and whether he would or not, he had not, as to them, revealed his pleaſure. And indeed the words of <hi>Job</hi> in his deſpair are the higheſt reaſoning of moſt Philoſophers,
<note place="margin">c. 14.10.</note> 
               <hi>Man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>dieth, and waſteth away; yea, man giveth up the Ghoſt, and where is he?</hi> And <hi>Solomon,</hi> in the perſon of a natural man, asks a queſtion, which he challengeth the World to anſwer,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>Who knoweth the ſpirit of a man that goeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the ſpirit of a beast that goeth downward to the Earth? Who knoweth? i.e.</hi> upon the principles of meer Reaſon, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearch of Natural Cauſes, who is able to reſolve it? Whereupon among the Jews,
<note place="margin">Act 23.8.</note> the <hi>Sadduces, who denied the Reſurrection,</hi> denied likewiſe both <hi>Angel and Spirit, i. e.</hi> the ſurviving of the ſoul, as well as the reſtoring of the body. So that ſince men do natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doubt of the leſs, it is no wonder if they deſpair of the greater? They who are apt to give the ſoul it ſelf for loſt, how can they imagine that the body ſhould ever be recovered?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Reaſon, why natural men are ſo apt to disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Reſurrection, is, becauſe they make a wrong eſtimate of <hi>Gods Power.</hi> We ſee in this World nothing better, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are ready to meaſure God by our ſelves; and believe no more of his Power than what falls within the compaſs of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105048:28"/>probability; which is the true and fixed ground of all that Atheiſtical Diſtruſt, which in all times doth ſo much abound among men: <hi>Who is the Lord,</hi> ſaid <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>that I ſhould let Iſrael go?</hi> And, <hi>Who is Jehova,</hi> ſaies Inſulting <hi>Senacherib,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reg 18.35.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhould deliver</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>out of my hand?</hi> Nay, not only theſe wicked men, but the Saints of old have moſt ſtumbled, when they have been put to Act Faith upon Gods Omnipotency;
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.11.</note> Thus <hi>Sarah</hi> when ſhe heard the promiſe of a <hi>Son, ſhe laughed, What,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>now I am old ſhall I have pleaſure, my Husband being old alſo?</hi> Wherein ſhe muſters up Arguments to make her Diſtruſt ſeem Rational. So <hi>Moſes</hi> finds out many excuſes to avoid being ſent upon Gods Errand, <hi>I am not Eloquent,</hi> faith he,
<note place="margin">Exod. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>but ſlow of ſpeech, and ſlow of Tongue;</hi> And at laſt, in plain terms, he entreats that God would find out a fitter Meſſenger to go upon his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie, And whence did this proceed,
<note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> but from his diſtruſt of Gods Power to Qualifie him firſt, and to Protect him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards? Thus <hi>David, Jeremy, Zachary,</hi> nay, almoſt all, when a ſtreſs or difficulty hath been laid upon their Faith, they have been ready to cry out, with <hi>Nicodemus, How can theſe things be?</hi> Thus it fares in the Caſe of the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> Men do firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the Omnipotence of God to their own Notions, and then deny what otherwiſe they would never have doubted of.
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.29.</note> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour therefore tells the unbelieving and gainſaying <hi>Sadduces, Ye erre, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God;</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, which declare the Reſurrection; nor the Power of God, which is able to effect it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Reaſon of this Unbelief is, becauſe Natural men are guided only by ſenſible Impreſſions; what they ſee, that they believe, and are not, without a great deal of difficulty, carried one jot farther. Hence were the Jews ſo importunate with our Saviour to ſhew them <hi>a ſign from Heaven;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.1.</note> And when our Saviour told fome of his Followers, in anſwer to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that it was <hi>the work of God, (i.e.</hi> well-pleaſing to,
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.30, 31.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by him) <hi>to believe on him, whom he had ſent.</hi> They preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reply upon him, <hi>What ſign ſhewſt thou then, that we may ſee and believe thee?</hi> So thoſe Scoffers in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> when the Propher had denounced terrible things againſt them, <hi>Let him make ſpeed,</hi> ſay they, <hi>and haſten his work, that we may ſee it.</hi> That is, you ſpeak
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105048:29"/>much to us of what ſhall come hereafter, but we ſee no danger near, and therefore we will not believe you. Thus thoſe wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Phariſees, when they had nailed our Saviour to the Croſs, <hi>Let him now,</hi> ſay they, <hi>come down from the Croſs, and we will believe him.</hi> Vain men as well as Cruel! Vain, in that they conceived it lay in their own Power to believe when they pleaſed; Cruel, in that they did inſult over a man, whom they had ſo inhumanely mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: Both Vain and Cruel, in that they could imagine our Saviour, after the Miracles of his Life, and more than miraculous Patience of his Death, fruitleſly ſhewn amongſt them, would now deſcend at laſt meerly to ſatisfie their Impious Curioſity. We are all of the Tormented Perſons mind;
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.30, 31.</note> though Preaching can do no good upon us, yet we think, if one came from the dead and taught us, we ſhould then certainly be converted; But our Saviour hath reſolved the Caſe clean otherwiſe, <hi>If they,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hear not</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets</hi> (who ſpeak in the Name of God with that Authority, as becomes his Power; and with that Purity, as becomes his Holineſs; if theſe men, thus ſpeaking, be not liſtened to) <hi>neither will men be perſwaded, though one roſe from the dead.</hi> So that our Saviour (who beſt underſtood all the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks and Methods of Perſwaſion) hath left it as an Eternal and Experienced Truth, That no <hi>Miracle</hi> can convince them whom the <hi>Word</hi> will not work upon; that Illuſtrations of Faith are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more ſatisfying than Impreſſions from ſenſe; ſince the one periſh preſently, and decay by uſing, but the other ſoak in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoul, and grow up into a kind of Connaturalneſs with it, moulding and faſhioning the mind unto their own temper, and every day adds freſh life and vigour to them. But a Natural man going not further than his Eye of natural Reaſon can carry him; having never ſeen any thing like to the Reſurrection, no wonder if he doth not believe it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt and true Reaſon, why Natural men do not believe the Reſurrection of the dead, is, becauſe they are unwilling to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it. It is harſh and ſevere Doctrine; It laies the Axe to the Root of the Tree of Self, and cuts off all our Fantaſtick Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; It is the Fan that blows away our Husky and Chaffie Pleaſures, and leaves us to fix upon nothing, but a ſolid and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Good. And therefore when one comes, and preſſes this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105048:29"/>cloſely upon us, we are ready to cry out, as the woman, when ſhe had loſt her Son, did to the Prophet, <hi>What have we to do with thee, O thou man of God, art thou come to call our ſins to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and to ſlay our Son, i.e.</hi> To kill and deſtroy our Pleaſures, which are the Darlings of our Soul? Hence it is, that either we fortifie our ſelves with Objections againſt the Reſurrection, as the Heathen world did, and take a great deal of pains to ſtrengthen our Unbelief; or elſe, like <hi>Felix,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> we run away from the ſound of it, for fear it ſhould put us into a fit of trembling. Should a man come and preach, as ſome among the Jews did, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall dye;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 22.13.</note> ſuch an one as this we ſhould welcome into our houſe, and thank him for his Poyſon. But let them call to us to <hi>repent, for the Kingdom of heaven is at hand;</hi> they will fare as <hi>John</hi> and our <hi>Saviour</hi> did; though they may ſcape with their Lives, yet they ſhall not eſcape our Cenſure. Let a <hi>Paul</hi> teach us, that <hi>now God commandeth all men every where to repent, becauſe he hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the World in Righteouſneſs, by that man whom he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi> This Doctrine ſo ſober in it ſelf, of ſo great concernment to the Party that hears it, and of ſo little to him that ſpeaks it, will yet be entertained with ſcorn and obloquy; <hi>Take him away, he is not fit to live,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 22.22.</note> ſaies the enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Jew; He is a <hi>Babler, and an impertinent Prater,</hi> ſaies the learned Athenian: <hi>A meer Fanatick,</hi> ſaies <hi>Festus;</hi> in ſhort, without enquiring whether the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> thus declared, be poſſible or not; we haſtily conclude that it is impoſſible; and upon that undoing Preſumption raſhly venture upon our own Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for the ſecond Obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> The Third Obſervation was, That the Doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, however Incredible it may ſeem to Natural men, yet it is in it ſelf highly credible, and may be evinced, even by that which Natural men do moſt pretend to, and that is Reaſon. Now the credibility of it will appear from theſe three Arguments:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is Poſſible, it may be; God can do it.</p>
            <p n="2">II. It is neceſſary, it muſt be; There is no Providence without it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105048:30"/> III. It is evident and certain that it hath been; and ſo hath been, as withal it demonſtratively proves that it ſhall be.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Argument, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> which proves the Doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furrection Credible, is the Poſſibility of it, it may be; and this muſt be well weighed, in oppoſition to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>How</hi> of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men, who think it implies a contradiction, that a body ſo ſcattered and diſperſed (one man ſometimes feeding upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo confounding the Integral parts of both) ſhould ever be reſtored again,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig.</hi> l. 2. &amp; 7.</note> and thence conclude it impoſſible; as <hi>Celſus</hi> the Epicurean Philoſopher, and others.</p>
            <p>Now the Reſurrection will appear poſſible, upon a twofold account.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In reſpect of God, who raiſeth the Body.</item>
               <item>2. In reſpect of the Body, which is raiſed by him.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Reſurrection is poſſible, in reſpect of God who rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Body; he is able to do it; which is intimated here by our Apoſtle, <hi>Why,</hi> ſaith he, is it judged incredible with you, that <hi>God ſhould raiſe the dead:</hi> As if he had ſaid, did we affirm, that the body of man, like Plants, did riſe by any Seminal and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifick vertue of its own, then none would wonder if you did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride and disbelieve us: But we teach no ſuch Doctrine, we only affirm, that <hi>God will raiſe the dead</hi> by an immediate Act of his Omnipotence: And then, why ſhould this appear <hi>incredible</hi> to you? For cannot God do whatever he pleaſes? What ſhould hinder him, that he cannot as well raiſe the Dead, as make the Living? It is with this, that God himſelf doth ſilence <hi>Sarahs</hi> ſcruples:
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.14.</note> 
               <hi>Is any thing too hard for the Lord?</hi> With this he doth repreſs <hi>Moſes</hi> Diffidence, <hi>Who hath made mans mouth? Or who maketh the deaf or dumb, the ſeeing or the blind? Is it not I the Lord?</hi> As if he had ſaid, I that have done the greater, am I not able to do the leſs? I who have made mans mouth, am not I able to diſpoſe and fit it for what ends I pleaſe? With this the Angel doth relieve <hi>Maries</hi> ſurprize and wonder,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.37.</note> when (upon the promiſe that ſhe ſhould conceive a child, without the knowledge of a man, which certainly was every whit as impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as that I am treating of) ſhe began to ſtagger and Heſitate a little, <hi>With God,</hi> ſaith the Angel, <hi>nothing ſhall be impoſſible;</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105048:30"/>for a further ſtrengthening of her Faith,
<note place="margin">Ver. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Elizabeth</hi> encourages her from her own experience, <hi>Bleſſed is ſhe that believeth; for there ſhall be a performance of thoſe things which were told her from the Lord.</hi> For, who is there that will preſume to ſet limits to Gods Power? Or, that dare ſay to an Almighty Agent, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to canſt thou come, but no farther? He that dares be guilty of ſo bold and blaſphemous an Aſſertion, muſt likewiſe allow this contradiction, that a Finite Agent can conceive the utmoſt of an Infinite and Incomprehenſible Perfection. As therefore in the Queſtion, concerning <hi>Mans Freewill,</hi> and <hi>Gods Predetermination</hi> of Future Contingencies, I have by experience found it, that the beſt way to reconcile theſe two, is to deny neither, but to charge all doubts upon <hi>Gods Omniſcience:</hi> For it is, and will be a doubt, which none but a Divine and All-knowing Underſtanding can reſolve, How Man ſhould <hi>Act Freely,</hi> (as we are conſcious to our ſelves that we do) and yet not the leaſt Action we do, but was <hi>Predeſtined</hi> by God from all Eternity; which not only plain Texts of Scripture, but the Truth of Philoſophy, and the bare ſeries and ſubordination of Cauſes doth clearly demonſtrate. Here, inſtead of tiring out our ſelves with vain Reaſoning, and Uncharitable Reviling; the ſafeſt and moſt prudent way is, to ſhelter our ſelves under <hi>Gods Omniſcience,</hi> for it is <hi>dignus Numine Nodus;</hi> and we cannot better diſcover our own Humility, or give God the glory of his Knowledge, than if we confeſs, that there are ſome things which only he can underſtand. So in the diſpute concerning the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> when doubts ariſe, as too often they will; and the more we think of it, the ſtronger and the more puzling will the Objections be; here the beſt way will be to have recourſe to <hi>Gods Omnipotence,</hi> and to believe firmly, that God is eaſily able to do more than Man can conceive. Thus did the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> anſwer thoſe Scoffers, who began to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether our Saviour would make good his Promiſe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judge the World: <hi>This,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3 5.</note> 
               <hi>they are willingly ignorant of, that by the Word of God the Heavens were made of old.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Theſe men have no reaſon to look upon Chriſts judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World, and deſtroying it by fire, as ſo incredible a thing; for when God made it out of nothing, he did produce a greater Wonder. So let us not doubt but God is able to recover our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105048:31"/>ſcattered Duſt, where ever it is lodged in the bowels of the Earth; who did extract this admirable Frame of all things out of the wombe of Nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reſurrection is Poſſible, in reſpect of the Body which is to be raiſed, for that hath already paſſed a greater change than the Reſurrection doth amount to: Since to paſs from nothing to ſomething is a much greater change, than barely to paſs from Death to Life: Yet one we have already experimented, and why ſhould we then doubt or deſpair of the other? This Holy men in Scripture do often reflect upon,
<note place="margin">c. 10.10, 11, 12, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Hast thou not,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, poured me out as Milk, and crudled me like Cheeſe; thon haſt cloathed me with Skin and Fleſh, and haſt fenced me with Bones and Sinews; Thou haſt granted me life,</hi> &amp;c. So that what he ſpeaks a little before,
<note place="margin">Ver. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Remember, I beſeech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay, and wilt thou bring me into dust again?</hi> may be inverted thus, <hi>God hath made us as the Clay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.14.</note> 
               <hi>and cannot he bring us out of the dust again?</hi> So <hi>David, I will praiſe thee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for I am fearfully and wonderfully made; my ſubſtance was not hid from thee, when I was made in ſecret, when I was curiouſly wrought in the loweſt parts of the Earth;</hi> wherein he eloquently deſcribes the wonderful Art whereby God had made him: And cannot he repair theſe buildings of fleſh and bloud with the ſame eaſe with which at firſt he reared them? Let him that doubts ask himſelf this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Was there not a time when once I was not! As <hi>David, My members in continuance,</hi> or <hi>ſucceſſively, were faſhioned, when as yet there was none of them.</hi> And as God, without my taking care, without the expence ſo much as of a Miracle did joyn and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment theſe pieces; did call for his Wind, and breath life into them; did put in a portion of his Spirit into them, and give them underſtanding: So when they are ſevered, cannot he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and reunite them? Eſpecially, ſince the Parts of our diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved earth they are ſcattered only, they are not loſt; Thrown up and down, in a ſeemingly careleſs manner, but ſtill they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eye of an All-ſeeing Providence, and laid up like ſacred Reliques, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in Gods ſtore-houſe,</hi> to be fetched out thence when the <hi>Heavens ſhall be no more;</hi> which is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Job</hi>'s Melancholy;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 14.12.</note> 
               <hi>Man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>lieth down, and riſeth not till the Heavens be no more they ſhall not awake, nor be raiſed out
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105048:31"/>of their ſleep.</hi> Now we are taught, that <hi>the Heavens ſhall be no more;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 3.</note> and that is the time appointed for this Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> The Second Argument which makes the Reſurrection ſeem credible, is from the neceſſity of it; It muſt be, there would be no Providence without it. For the Reſurrection ſerves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate two prime Attributes of God, without which neither God could be honoured, not the World governed.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It demonſtrates Gods Mercy.</item>
               <item>2. It demonſtrates Gods Juſtice.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Reſurrection demonſtrates Gods Mercy: For God hath appointed this order in the World, that every thing ſhould have a kind of Reſurrection. <hi>The Sun,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, ariſeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 1.5, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and the Sun goeth down, and haſteneth to the place where he aroſe.</hi> And, <hi>Unto the place from whence the Rivers came, thither they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again.</hi> Thus Day dies into Night, and Night riſes into Day: Winter is the Death of the Year, and Spring is its Reſurrection. And many more ſuch like inſtances there are in Nature. Now it would not be ſuited to the Grace and Mercy of our God, that every thing ſhould <hi>ſuos patimanes, have its Turns and Returns,</hi> and the Nobleſt Creature of all, Man, ſhould be altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted! That every thing elſe ſhould have alternate changes, and be repaired by dying, and Mans body only ſhould be huddled up in the Horrour of Eternal Night! Sure that merciful Father, who ſhewed ſo much curious Architecture in contriving this Body, did not intend it ſhould Act a Part only upon this ſhort Scene of Life; for then certainly he would not have conjoyned it with a Gueſt which looks and breaths after nothing but Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality. Our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Joh. 12.24.</note> prophecying of that Progreſs his Goſpel ſhould make after his deceaſe, compares himſelf to <hi>a Corn of Wheat, which if it fall into the ground,and dye not, it abideth alone: but if it dye, it bringeth forth much fruit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.36.</note> And the Apoſtle, when that queſtion was asked, <hi>How are the Dead raiſed up?</hi> Replies preſently, <hi>Thou Fool, that which thou ſoweſt is not quickened except it dye;</hi> implying it to be nothing elſe but direct Folly, to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that which in a thing ſo obvious as the ſowing of Corn, might be concluded not only Poſſible but Neceſſary: Since Man is beyond many grains, and more eſpecially the Object of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Gods care and Compaſſion: For whoſe Inſtruction he hath
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105048:32"/>ſcattered about the World ſo many Preludiums and Rudiments of <hi>a better Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reſurrection is neceſſary, becauſe it demonſtrates Gods Juſtice. Were it not for Future Judgment, nothing would be ſo full of Confuſion and Diſorder as the World. This Earth, in the preſent Polity and Frame of it; is nothing elſe but a meer Chaos, where Vice and Iniquity thrive, as in their own ſoyl, but Virtue and Piety do find neither Place nor Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That day of Reckoning to be reveal'd in Fire, which muſt abſolve Providence, and ſcatter thoſe Miſts wherewith the beauty of it is now obſcured and ſtained. It is this that muſt ſtop men in their Carier of ſin, and keep them honeſt in the dark: For in that ſacred Irony of the Wiſe man, <hi>Rejoyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>O young man, in thy youth, and walk in the waies of thy heart. and in the ſight of thy eyes: but know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to judgement;</hi> which is all one as if he had ſaid, Go young man, ſin if thou dareſt, for thou muſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after come to judgement.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.2.</note> In this world, <hi>All things come alike to all;</hi> God ſcatters his good things with an undiſtinguiſhing hand, <hi>tanquam Miſſilia Coeli,</hi> as <hi>his Largeſſes,</hi> and ſigns of his promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bounty, rather than marks of his eſpecial Love. But future Judgement is Gods ſevering time, called by the Apoſtle, the time <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> i.e. <hi>of ſetting all things right;</hi> of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing every thing upon its proper Baſis, and giving all their due. Now to this the Reſurrection of the body is neceſſary, <hi>For we must all appear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 55.10.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, before the Judgement-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that he hath done, whether it be good or evill.</hi> In the Law we find, <hi>That the ſoul that ſinneth must dye;</hi> and it is moſt juſt, that the body which did joyn in the ſin, ſhould likewiſe partake in the puniſhment. Thoſe dear Allies were not ſeparated in their good or evill doing, and therefore there is no reaſon they ſhould be diſtinct in their Reward. <hi>I carry about me,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>the dying of the Lord Jeſus, (i.e.</hi> I lead a kind of dying and Calamitous life for his ſake) <hi>that ſo the life alſo of Jeſus might be manifeſted in my mortal Fleſh.</hi> In requital of all our Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<note place="margin">2 Joh 8.</note> Impriſonments, Faſtings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if the ſoul only ſhould be glorified, <hi>we ſhould not have a full reward;</hi> which it is our duty to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105048:32"/>look after. And therefore this Hand, this Tongue, this Eye, This, whatever it is, whereby God hath been either provoked or honoured, ſhall be quickned again, and put into the poſſeſſion of a never-dying life, and fitted for the enjoyment of eternal either Joy or Torment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> The Laſt Argument which makes the Doctrine of the Reſurrection credible, is from the evidence and certainty of it, ſince it hath been ſo, as that withall it neceſſarily implies that it ſhall be. For Chriſt is Riſen, and taken poſſeſſion of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not only for himſelf, but for his Followers.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>Now if Chriſt be preached,</hi> as the Apoſtle argues, <hi>that he roſe from the Dead, how ſay ſome among you, that there is no Reſurrection of the dead?</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. <hi>Garbut.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt.</note> As if he had ſaid, If you barely conſidered the Reſurrection in it ſelf, you might then have ſomething to plead in the excuſe of your Unbelief, but ſince <hi>Chriſt is Riſen,</hi> there is no longer any room left for the leaſt diſpute about it. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> is riſen, either as a <hi>Judge,</hi> or as an <hi>Head;</hi> and therefore all muſt riſe, the wicked, to be condemned; the faithful, to be ſaved by him.</p>
            <p>The Uſe of this may ſerve to demonſtrate two things:
<list>
                  <item>1. The Reaſonableneſs of Chriſtian Faith.</item>
                  <item>2. The Neceſſity of Chriſtian Life.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> This ſerves to demonſtrate the Reaſonableneſs of Chriſtian Faith: As when God would convince the Heathen, that their Idols were not Gods, he challenges them to produce their <hi>ſtrong Reaſons,</hi> and to prove their Cauſe by Arguments: <hi>Shew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 41.23.</note> ſaith he, <hi>the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are Gods; yea, do good, or do evill, that we may be diſmaied, i.e.</hi> If ye are indeed, as your Worſhippers ſuppoſe, Gods, then ſhew it by thoſe infallible and unalterable ſigns of a Diety, <hi>viz.</hi> Your <hi>Preſcience,</hi> and your <hi>Power.</hi> So may a Chriſtian ſay in this Caſe, he may and ought to challenge the unbelieving World to <hi>produce their ſtrong Reaſons</hi> to declare their Cauſe, and to ſee whether they have ſo much to ſay, even in point of Reaſon, for the moſt clear and un queſtioned part of their Opinion, as we have for the moſt contradicted of ours. For a Chriſtian ſhould not ſatisfie himſelf with a bare and naked Faith, grounding himſelf either upon Tradition, or the credit of his Teachers, but he ſhould labour for himſelf If to know both what, and why he believes. It is a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105048:33"/>general Rule the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> gives,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye alwaies ready to give an account of your Faith to every one that asks you.</hi> And our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our though he did preſs his Followers to believe on him; yet he never did require from them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig.</hi> lib. 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then falſly objected: i.e. <hi>An unreaſonable and Untried Faith;</hi> but where ever he gives the Command, he alleadges at the ſame time Reaſons ſufficient to convince the moſt obſtinate gainſayer, ſuch are the heavenlineſs of his Language,
<note place="margin">Joh. 15.22.</note> 
               <hi>Had I not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>come and ſpoke unto them, they had not had ſin; but now they have no cloak for their ſin;</hi> For his words, by their own confeſſion, <hi>were ſuch as never any man ſpake,</hi> and carried a clear Reſemblance to the body he took, as being moſt humble in ſtile, and moſt ſublime in ſenſe.
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.</note> And therefore he complains of them, <hi>Why,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do ye not know</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>diſcern who I am by my manner of diſcourſe amongst you;</hi> for certainly ſuch words could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from one who came to deceive the world; as thoſe replied, <hi>Theſe are not the words of him that hath a devil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10.21.</note> Another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument our Saviour uſes to induce them to believe was his <hi>Works,</hi> which <hi>Nicodemus</hi> confeſſeth were ſuch <hi>as never any man did.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 5.36.</note> And our Saviour doth often appeal to their Teſtimony, as where he ſaies, <hi>I have a greater witneſs than that of</hi> John, <hi>for the works which the Father hath given me to finiſh, the ſame works that I do, bear witneſs of me, that the Father hath ſent me.</hi> And again, <hi>If I had not done among them the works which no other man did,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15.24.</note> 
               <hi>they had not had ſin.</hi> But, that which our Saviour moſt inſiſted upon was the Scriptures, to them he refers the Jews; out of theſe do the Apoſtles altogether argue; and to the ſearch of theſe are all conjoyn'd; and ſtill we can ground our belief upon their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, whatever we boaſt of is not <hi>Faith</hi> but <hi>Fancy,</hi> and will not hold out in a time of Triall. Then the ſoul can only ſit down ſatisfied, when by comparing the <hi>Predictions</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> with the <hi>fulfillings</hi> of the <hi>New,</hi> it can ſubſcribe <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumeſt,</hi> I have examined, and find it true.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe this is a matter of very great importance, and yet too much neglected, therefore I ſhall preſs it upon theſe Conſiderations:</p>
            <p n="1">1. This will ſweeten our Obedience. Till we are ſatisfied as Men, we can never obey as Chriſtians: For Faith is nothing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105048:33"/>elſe but another kind of Reaſon, whoſe Baſis and Foundation is laid in humility: Therefore the Apoſtle calls that great Action of a Chriſtian, when he doth not, as in the Old Law, ſacrifice an Oxe, but himſelf up to God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ſervice ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us as reaſonable Creatures.</hi> In things of Art, the hands will not do what the head doth not direct; ſo in ſpiritual things, we quite miſtake our way, if we think of going blindfold and hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winck'd to Duty. Ignorance and Implicite Obedience is a fit Sacrifice for the devil, whoſe kingdom is founded in darkneſs, when as <hi>Regeneration</hi> is nothing elſe but <hi>renewed Light:</hi> And the clearer Diſcoveries are made to the Underſtanding, the more pliant and obedient is the Will,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> and the more eaſie doth it find the Yoke. For this end, is Preaching and Propheſying in a known Tongue commanded, that there might be a Race of knowing Chriſtians. And <hi>Paul</hi> would not ſo much as <hi>Sing,</hi> or <hi>Pray,</hi> or do any other Act of Religious Worſhip, with his <hi>Spirit</hi> only, but with his Underſtanding alſo. There cannot be a greater brand caſt upon any ones devotion, than <hi>to worſhip they know not what;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 4.22.</note> for that is that which our Saviour doth eſpecially blame the <hi>Samaritans</hi> for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the beſt way to win upon others. And this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concerns Miniſters of the Goſpel; whom I may ask, in the Apoſtles words: <hi>Thou that teacheſt another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>wilt thou not teach thy ſelf?</hi> Thou who commandeſt another to believe, wilt thou not give him a Reaſon, why he ſhould believe, and ſo leave him without excuſe?
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> Thus the Apoſtle bids <hi>Timothy</hi> be an example to the Faithful, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>in reaſoning:</hi> and gives this general charge, that <hi>a man of God muſt be apt to teach, in meekneſs instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thoſe that oppoſe themſelves.</hi> There are indeed ſome men of <hi>diſeaſed minds,</hi> who have quenched in themſelves all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, by which they may recover and be enlightened. But there are in the World many ſober Diſſenters, who ſtand off from embracing Chriſtianity, meerly from the apprehenſions they have, that the Tenets of it are Abſurd and Unreaſonable;
<note place="margin">Act. 17.20.</note> ſuch as theſe muſt be won by Argument. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> dealt with the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who, when they deſired to be better informed of his Doctrine, he makes a moſt excellent diſcourſe to them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Providence, and clears by unanſwerable Reaſon, that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105048:34"/>their way of Worſhip was falſe, becauſe it begot in mens minds low and mean opinions of the Deity, as if he were confined to Place, or did take delight in outward Repreſentations. Thus did our Saviour deal with <hi>Nicodemus.</hi> In ſhort, Ignorance in a Goſpel-Teacher is a capital crime; for our Saviour, when ever he preached, he did it with this Preface, <hi>Hear and Underſtand;</hi> and when his Diſciples, were ſomewhat dull of Apprehenſion, he ſharply reproves them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>What are you,</hi> whom I deſign to be Lights and Guides of the World <hi>without Underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The want of this, is the cauſe why Chriſtians ſtand ſo much at a ſtay, and make no better Progreſs. Total Ignorance is a certain ſign of Perdition,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>If our Goſpel,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>be hid,</hi> it is hid <hi>to them that are lost.</hi> Partial Ignorance is a ſign of weakneſs, for there is that Light, that Evidence in our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if it be followed, it will alwaies fill the mind with freſh Diſcoveries. They who firſt read the Scriptures, are like ſuch that ſee a glorious Palace at a diſtance, it is wrapped up in a Miſt, and the Beauty of it lies concealed; but the nearer we approach, &amp; the more intently we view it, the more is the Luſtre of it manifeſted. The World, <hi>i.e.</hi> Carnal men, do count the Goſpel <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Idoll, and a <hi>Fooliſh thing;</hi> but <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, and all true Believers find it to be <hi>the Wiſdome of God,</hi> a Plot laid from all Eternity; for the effecting of which the World was made; and when the Myſtery of Salvation, there declared, is perfected, the World ſhall be laid aſide as an uſeleſs Scene. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to invite our Study, doth ſtile himſelf <hi>the Light of the World;</hi> and who doth not ſee, that all who are not enlightned by him are covered with Darkneſs, Uncertainty, and doubting? But <hi>John</hi> calls our Saviour <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i.e.</hi> in the proper ſignification of the word, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> he being that Eternal Fountain, from whom true Reaſon ſprung; and by whom our loſt and ruin'd Reaſon is repaired.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſearcheth the depths of God; i.e.</hi> the Spirit of God in man, makes him unquiet and reſtleſs in his ſearch, till he hath ſounded thoſe depths, which the Ignorant and Lazy World paſs haſtily over. How eaſily by this light would thoſe Miſts, about <hi>Incarnation, Providence, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> &amp;c. which to this day perplex the diſputing world, be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105048:34"/>all diſperſed and ſcattered? As to this laſt, the Apoſtle here is very Poſitive, that he would venture all upon a Diſpute, and that the beſt reaſon ſhould carry it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond Uſe is to ſhew the Neceſſity of Chriſtian Life; and this is ſo clear from the Premiſes, that it need not be long inſiſted on. For, <hi>If the Dead riſe not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.32.</note> the conſequence which <hi>Paul</hi> brings in wicked men making is very Natural, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall dye.</hi> But if the dead riſe, then <hi>Peter</hi> hath made a Rational Inference,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>The end of all things is at hand, let us be ſober, and watch unto Prayer.</hi> For the time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when <hi>the hidden things of our ſhame ſhall be brought to light;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> this certainly, if once believed, would keep us honeſt in the dark; one Sermon about it made <hi>Felix</hi> tremble, though, being a Roman, his Unbelief made him careleſs; and his calling valiant. Did but men once give themſelves leave to think of it, they would not ſo ſpend their daies, as if they had nothing but this Inch of time to provide for. For as our ſouls are alwaies on the wing; ſo our bodies are not entirely our own; but hereafter to be reſumed again, and made either Cages for Unclean, or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for Clorified Spirits. And therefore that unchangeable ſtate, into which they ſhall once paſs, is by all wiſe and knowing men moſt to be ſecured. So that I ſhall conclude in the words of the Prophet <hi>Hoſea: Who is wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.9.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſhall underſtand theſe things? Prudent, and he ſhall know them? For the waies of the Lord are right, and the Juſt ſhall walk in them: but the Tranſgreſſour ſhall fall therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 16. Line 2. <hi>by yet more,</hi> r. <hi>yet more, by.</hi> p. 13. l. 24. <hi>doctrine dangerous,</hi> r. <hi>doctrine is dangerous.</hi> Ib. l. 26. <hi>have,</hi> r. <hi>leave.</hi> p. 18. l. 7. <hi>Regimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> r. <hi>Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> p. 24. l. 34. <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> r. <hi>deſcryed.</hi> p. 25. l. 13 <hi>Bounds</hi> r. <hi>Mounds.</hi> p. 27 l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 32. l. 19. <hi>deſire</hi> r. <hi>deſired.</hi> p. 56. l. 28. <hi>ſtill</hi> r. <hi>till.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
